const arr = [{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following gives rise to the trigone of the bladder?","answers":[{"option":"Paramesonephric duct","bool":false},{"option":"Splanchnic mesoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Mullerian duct","bool":false},{"option":"Endoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Mesonephric duct","bool":true}],"id":0},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is involved in the counter-current multiplier mechanism of kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false},{"option":"Peritubular arteries","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":true}],"id":1},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the type of epithelium lining the ureters?","answers":[{"option":"Simple squamous epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Stratified squamous non-keratinized epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Transitional epithelium","bool":true},{"option":"Stratified squamous keratinized epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Pseudostratified columnar epithelium","bool":false}],"id":2},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following parts of the nephron is involved in the facultative reabsorption of water?","answers":[{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Duct of Bellini","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":3},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2017","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which type of epithelium lines the proximal convoluted tubules?","answers":[{"option":"Transitional epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Simple cuboidal epithelium","bool":true},{"option":"Pseudostratified columnar epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Simple squamous epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Simple columnar epithelium","bool":false}],"id":4},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is formed as a result of deamination of cytosine?","answers":[{"option":"Methyl cytosine","bool":false},{"option":"Adenine","bool":false},{"option":"Uracil","bool":true},{"option":"Cytidylic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Tyrosine","bool":false}],"id":5},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Erythropoietin is primarily formed in which organ?","answers":[{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false},{"option":"Brain","bool":false},{"option":"Kidneys","bool":true},{"option":"Liver","bool":false}],"id":6},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is a complication of acute pyelonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Papillary necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Necrotic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Cholecystitis","bool":false},{"option":"Pulmonary embolism","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic renal faillure","bool":false}],"id":7},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is diagnostic of acute gout?","answers":[{"option":"Acute phase reactants","bool":false},{"option":"Monosodium urate crystals on joint aspiration","bool":true},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Serum uric acid levels","bool":false},{"option":"Radiology of joint","bool":false}],"id":8},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the most sensitive indicator of glomerular function?","answers":[{"option":"Serum ammonia","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine clearance","bool":true},{"option":"Serum creatinine","bool":false},{"option":"Serum urea","bool":false},{"option":"Urea clearance","bool":false}],"id":9},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is not derived from ureteric bud?","answers":[{"option":"Ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder","bool":true},{"option":"Calyx","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false}],"id":10},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2021","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"An increase in which of the following leads to a subsequent decrease in the glomerular filtration rate?","answers":[{"option":"Peritubular capillary hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular capillary hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular capillary plasma oncotic pressure","bool":true},{"option":"Bowman's capsule plasma oncotic pressure","bool":false}],"id":11},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following hormones or autocoids can increase the glomerular filtration rate (GFR) by decreasing vascular resistance in the glomerular capillaries?","answers":[{"option":"Endothelial derived nitric oxide","bool":true},{"option":"Angiotensin II","bool":false},{"option":"Norepinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Epinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Angiotensin I","bool":false}],"id":12},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"The antidiuretic hormone controls water permeability in the collecting ducts of the kidney by regulation of which of the following water channels?","answers":[{"option":"Aquaporin-4","bool":false},{"option":"Aquaporin-1","bool":false},{"option":"Aquaporin-5","bool":false},{"option":"Aquaporin-2","bool":true},{"option":"Aquaporin-3","bool":false}],"id":13},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is a carbonic anhydrase inhibitor?","answers":[{"option":"Torsemide","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Acetazolamide","bool":true},{"option":"Furosemide","bool":false},{"option":"Bumetanide","bool":false}],"id":14},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"What part of the nephron lies in the renal cortex?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Medullary collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Thin ascending limb","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Thin descending limb","bool":false}],"id":15},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a property of ascending limb of the loop of Henle?","answers":[{"option":"Permeability to water is affected by antidiuretic hormone","bool":false},{"option":"Permeable to water","bool":false},{"option":"Impermeable to water","bool":true},{"option":"Impermeable to sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Impermeable to potassium","bool":false}],"id":16},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Renal blood flow (RBF) approximates how much of the total cardiac output?","answers":[{"option":"45-50%","bool":false},{"option":"1-2%","bool":false},{"option":"20-25%","bool":true},{"option":"30-50%","bool":false},{"option":"10-15%","bool":false}],"id":17},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the effect of aldosterone on kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"Increases Na+ and Cl- reabsorption, and K+ excretion","bool":true},{"option":"Decreases Na+ and Cl- reabsorption, and K+ excretion","bool":false},{"option":"Increases Na+ and K+ reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Increases Na+ and Cl- excretion, and K+ reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Increases Na+, Cl-, and K+ excretion","bool":false}],"id":18},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"What supports the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Perinephric fascia","bool":true},{"option":"Median arcuate ligament","bool":false},{"option":"Peritoneal fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Greater omentum","bool":false},{"option":"Lesser omentum","bool":false}],"id":19},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"How does atrial natriuretic peptide (ANP) increase sodium excretion?","answers":[{"option":"Increases glomerular filtration rate (GFR)","bool":true},{"option":"Constricts efferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Causes vasodilation of the afferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Decreases glomerular filtration rate (GFR)","bool":false},{"option":"Decreases Na+ channels in principal cells","bool":false}],"id":20},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following cells undergo developmental disturbance in severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID)?","answers":[{"option":"NK cells only","bool":false},{"option":"T cells and B cells","bool":false},{"option":"NK cells, B cells, and T cells","bool":true},{"option":"T cells only","bool":false},{"option":"NK cells and B cells","bool":false}],"id":21},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is deficient in severe combined immunodeficiency (SCID)?","answers":[{"option":"WASP gene","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocyte receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Adenosine deaminase","bool":true},{"option":"Bruton tyrosine kinase","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":22},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which part of the kidney can not have stones?","answers":[{"option":"Ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Calyces","bool":false},{"option":"Nephron","bool":true},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false}],"id":23},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most reliable diagnostic test for urolithiasis?","answers":[{"option":"Computed tomography","bool":true},{"option":"Intravenous pyelogram (IVP)","bool":false},{"option":"X-ray","bool":false},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Blood test","bool":false}],"id":24},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following amino acids donates nitrogen in both purine and pyrimidine synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Aspartate","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamine","bool":true},{"option":"Glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Valine","bool":false}],"id":25},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 2nd-year student is studying kidney anatomy and finds out that there are some structures anterior to the right kidney. Which of the following is not found anterior to the right kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Pylorus","bool":true},{"option":"2nd part of duodenum","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatic flexure","bool":false},{"option":"Right colic flexure","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false}],"id":26},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"A 9-year-old boy is brought to the clinic with complaints of cola-colored urine and reduced urine output for the past 2 days. He has a past history of being treated for a sore throat infection 3 weeks ago. His blood pressure is 145/95 mmHg. Urinalysis reveals red cell casts. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":true},{"option":"Goodpasture's syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Membranous nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Alport syndrome","bool":false}],"id":27},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"In which of the following organs does purine de novo synthesis not occur?","answers":[{"option":"Muscle","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Brain","bool":true}],"id":28},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not formed by the urogenital sinus?","answers":[{"option":"Seminal vesicle","bool":true},{"option":"Penile urethra","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Bulbourethral gland","bool":false},{"option":"Prostate gland","bool":false}],"id":29},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following restricts the ascent of a horseshoe kidney into the abdomen?","answers":[{"option":"Urinary bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Abdominal aortic bifurcation","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior mesenteric artery (IMA)","bool":true},{"option":"Superior mesenteric artery (SMA)","bool":false}],"id":30},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Nephrotic syndrome is characterized by loss of how much protein in urine?","answers":[{"option":">9.4 g/day","bool":false},{"option":">5.7 g/day","bool":false},{"option":">30 g/day","bool":false},{"option":">50 g/day","bool":false},{"option":">3.5 g/day","bool":true}],"id":31},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the normal value of glomerular filtration rate (GFR)?","answers":[{"option":"100 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"150 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"155 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"125 ml/min","bool":true},{"option":"175 ml/min","bool":false}],"id":32},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Net filtration pressure (NFP) is the total pressure that promotes filtration in kidneys. What is its value?","answers":[{"option":"10 mmHg","bool":true},{"option":"15 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"30 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"25 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"20 mmHg","bool":false}],"id":33},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Where is the micturition reflex center located?","answers":[{"option":"Hypothalamus","bool":false},{"option":"Rostral pontine tegmentum","bool":true},{"option":"Spinal cord","bool":false},{"option":"Medulla oblongata","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebellum","bool":false}],"id":34},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the optimum pH for pepsin?","answers":[{"option":"4.0","bool":false},{"option":"5.0","bool":false},{"option":"2.5","bool":true},{"option":"6.7","bool":false},{"option":"11.5","bool":false}],"id":35},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the value of the glomerular filtration rate below which it is classified as an end-stage renal disease (ESRD)?","answers":[{"option":"60 mL/min","bool":false},{"option":"30 mL/min","bool":false},{"option":"75 mL/min","bool":false},{"option":"15 mL/min","bool":true},{"option":"45 mL/min","bool":false}],"id":36},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Ureters develop from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Ureteric bud from mesonephric duct","bool":true},{"option":"Ureteric bud from metanephric duct","bool":false},{"option":"Mesenchymal condensation posterior to cloaca","bool":false},{"option":"Ureteric bud from allantois","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":37},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of these is not an isotonic solution?","answers":[{"option":"0.9% normal saline","bool":false},{"option":"5% dextrose","bool":false},{"option":"3% normal saline","bool":true},{"option":"Lactated ringer's solution","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":38},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the extension of the cortex in the renal medulla called?","answers":[{"option":"Renal columns","bool":true},{"option":"Renal pyramids","bool":false},{"option":"Medullary rays","bool":false},{"option":"Major calices","bool":false},{"option":"Minor calices","bool":false}],"id":39},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of acute renal failure?","answers":[{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Renal papillary necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Polycystic kidney disease","bool":false},{"option":"Acute interstitial nephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased blood flow to kidney","bool":false}],"id":40},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Synthetic compound allopurinol given to treat hyperuricemia is an analog of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Cytosine","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoxanthine","bool":true},{"option":"Orotic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Thymine","bool":false},{"option":"Inosine","bool":false}],"id":41},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a histological feature of the renal cortex?","answers":[{"option":"Simple cuboidal epithelium with brush border lining the proximal convulated tubules","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Cuboidal epithelium lining the bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Simple columnar epithelium with brush border lining the distal convulated tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus containing podocytes","bool":false}],"id":42},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following correctly states the osmolarity of the fluid entering  the proximal convoluted tubules?","answers":[{"option":"400 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"800 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"300 mOsm/L","bool":true},{"option":"1200 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"100 mOsm/L","bool":false}],"id":43},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of these is present on urinalysis in a patient with glomerulonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Hyaline cast","bool":false},{"option":"Granular cast","bool":false},{"option":"Red cell cast","bool":true},{"option":"Renal tubular cell cast","bool":false},{"option":"White cell cast","bool":false}],"id":44},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is the approximate value of the osmolarity of the interstitial fluid in renal medulla?","answers":[{"option":"600 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"1200 mOsm/L","bool":true},{"option":"200 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"800 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"400 mOsm/L","bool":false}],"id":45},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Increase in which of the following characterizes metabolic alkalosis?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma pH and increased lactate levels","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma pH and decreased CO2 levels","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma pH and increased respiratory rate","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma pH and decrease in HCO3- levels","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma pH and increased plasma bicarbonate (HCO3-) levels","bool":true}],"id":46},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following drugs should be used to decrease intracranial pressure?","answers":[{"option":"Mannitol","bool":true},{"option":"Fludrocortisone","bool":false},{"option":"Acetaminophen","bool":false},{"option":"Phenylephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Midodrine","bool":false}],"id":47},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following will increase the ability of the kidney to excrete concentrated urine?","answers":[{"option":"Increasing the rate of flow through the loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Decreasing the rate of blood flow through the medulla","bool":true},{"option":"Decreasing the permeability of the proximal tubule to water","bool":false},{"option":"Decreasing the permeability of the collecting duct to water","bool":false},{"option":"Decreasing the activity of the Na-K pump in the loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":48},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Na⁺/K⁺/2Cl⁻ co-transporter is present at which part of the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Collecting tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Ascending limb of loop of Henle","bool":true},{"option":"Descending limb of loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":49},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following can not be used as a marker to measure glomerular filtration rate (GFR)?","answers":[{"option":"Creatinine","bool":false},{"option":"Mannitol","bool":false},{"option":"Phenol red","bool":false},{"option":"Urea and nitrogen","bool":true},{"option":"Inulin","bool":false}],"id":50},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the normal value of filtration fraction?","answers":[{"option":"10%","bool":false},{"option":"15%","bool":false},{"option":"7%","bool":false},{"option":"20%","bool":true},{"option":"5%","bool":false}],"id":51},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common complication of catheterization?","answers":[{"option":"Infection","bool":true},{"option":"Toxic shock syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Anaphylaxis","bool":false},{"option":"Delayed hemolytic reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Febrile reaction","bool":false}],"id":52},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What parts of the nephron lie in the renal cortex?","answers":[{"option":"Glomeruli, bowman's capsule and loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pyramid, glomeruli, and bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Glomeruli, bowman's capsule and renal papilla","bool":false},{"option":"Renal corpuscles, proximal and distal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Collecting tubule, proximal and distal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":53},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"An 8-year-old boy presents to the outpatient department with complaints of headache, dizziness, malaise, having high blood pressure (B.P), and hematuria. He has a history of throat infection 3 weeks ago. What is the probable diagnosis of his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Membranous glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Wegener's granulomatosis","bool":false},{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":false}],"id":54},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the most common causative organism for acute pyelonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":true},{"option":"Enterobacter","bool":false},{"option":"Pseudomonas aeroginosa","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus mirabilis","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false}],"id":55},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What effect does exogenous erythropoietin have on a patient who has end-stage renal disease with anemia?","answers":[{"option":"Decreased blood volume","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Induces hypoxia","bool":false},{"option":"Increased blood pressure","bool":true},{"option":"Decreased erythrocyte production","bool":false}],"id":56},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"The hilum of the kidney is located in which plane?","answers":[{"option":"Median plane","bool":false},{"option":"Supine plane","bool":false},{"option":"Transpyloric plane","bool":true},{"option":"Transtubercular plane","bool":false},{"option":"Subcostal plane","bool":false}],"id":57},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the end-product of purine metabolism?","answers":[{"option":"Uric acid","bool":true},{"option":"Ammonia","bool":false},{"option":"Guanine","bool":false},{"option":"Uracil","bool":false},{"option":"Urea","bool":false}],"id":58},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Carbamoyl phosphate synthetase II (CPS-II) is allosterically inhibited by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Adenosine triphosphate (ATP)","bool":false},{"option":"Uridine monophosphate (UMP)","bool":false},{"option":"Uridine diphosphate (UDP)","bool":false},{"option":"Uridine triphosphate (UTP)","bool":true},{"option":"Phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate (PRPP)","bool":false}],"id":59},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the precursor of adenine monophosphate and guanine monophosphate ?","answers":[{"option":"Phosphoribosyl triphosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Orotate","bool":false},{"option":"Uric acid","bool":false},{"option":"Inosine monophosphate (IMP)","bool":true},{"option":"Glutamine","bool":false}],"id":60},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"During degradation of purine nucleotides to uric acid, inosine monophosphate and guanosine monophosphate are broken down by which of the following enzymes?","answers":[{"option":"Ribonucleotide reductase","bool":false},{"option":"Adenosine deaminase","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"5'-nucleotidase","bool":true},{"option":"Guanylate kinase","bool":false}],"id":61},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Aspartate enters the tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA cycle) in the form of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Oxaloacetate","bool":true},{"option":"Succinic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha-ketoglutarate","bool":false},{"option":"Citrate","bool":false},{"option":"Fumarate","bool":false}],"id":62},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of pyelonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Staphylococcus saprophyticus","bool":false},{"option":"Klebsiella species","bool":false},{"option":"E. coli","bool":true},{"option":"Enterococcus faecalis","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus mirabilis","bool":false}],"id":63},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which is true about creatinine during glomerular filtration at normal levels?","answers":[{"option":"Secreted by the tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Excreted by the tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Neither secreted nor reabsorbed by the tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Secreted and reabsorbed by the tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Reabsorbed by the tubule","bool":false}],"id":64},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Where does the hilum of the left kidney lie?","answers":[{"option":"The subcostal plane","bool":false},{"option":"The interspinous plane","bool":false},{"option":"The junction of midclavicular line and the transtubercular plane","bool":false},{"option":"The transpyloric plane, 5 cm from the median plane","bool":true},{"option":"The transtubercular plane, 5 cm from the median plane","bool":false}],"id":65},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following organisms is responsible for xanthogranulomatous pyelonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Klebsiella","bool":false},{"option":"Salmonella","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus","bool":true},{"option":"Neisseria gonorrhoeae","bool":false},{"option":"E. coli","bool":false}],"id":66},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Reabsorption of sodium in renal tubules is associated with the exchange of which of these ions?","answers":[{"option":"Na+ ions","bool":false},{"option":"HCO3- ions","bool":false},{"option":"H+ ions","bool":false},{"option":"K+ ions","bool":true},{"option":"Cl- ions","bool":false}],"id":67},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Penile urethra is mainly formed from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Surface ectoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Vesical part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Phallic part of urogenital sinus","bool":true}],"id":68},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is not present anterior to the urinary bladder?","answers":[{"option":"Pubic bones","bool":false},{"option":"Puboprostatic ligament","bool":false},{"option":"Body of uterus","bool":true},{"option":"Retropubic space","bool":false},{"option":"Pubo-vesical ligament","bool":false}],"id":69},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the compensatory mechanism in respiratory acidosis (increased PCO2)?","answers":[{"option":"Decrease in plasma bicarbonate (HCO3-) concentration","bool":false},{"option":"Increased oxygen saturation","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased levels of ammonia","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in plasma bicarbonate (HCO3-) concentration","bool":true},{"option":"Decreased respiratory rate","bool":false}],"id":70},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which enzyme catalyzes the rate-limiting step of pyrimidine biosynthesis in mammalian cells?","answers":[{"option":"Carbamoyl phosphate synthase II","bool":true},{"option":"Thymidylate synthase","bool":false},{"option":"Aspartate transcarbamoylase","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyltransferase (HGPRT)","bool":false}],"id":71},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the renal capillary pressure across the glomerular capillaries?","answers":[{"option":"50 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"20 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"10 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"30 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"60 mmHg","bool":true}],"id":72},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"The superior portion of the ureter drains into which of the following lymph nodes?","answers":[{"option":"Internal iliac nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Common iliac nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral aortic nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Vesical nodes","bool":false},{"option":"External iliac nodes","bool":false}],"id":73},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following cells release the enzyme renin?","answers":[{"option":"Juxtaglomerular cells","bool":true},{"option":"Interstitial kidney cells","bool":false},{"option":"Parietal epithelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Brush border cells","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus parietal cells","bool":false}],"id":74},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is an acquired cause of vesicoureteral reflux in adults leading to urinary tract infection?","answers":[{"option":"Spinal cord lesions","bool":true},{"option":"Bladder stones","bool":false},{"option":"Prostate hypertrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Bacterial infection","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney stones","bool":false}],"id":75},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following structures is only found in the renal medulla?","answers":[{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Minor calyces","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Thin limb of loop of Henle","bool":true}],"id":76},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Mycophenolic acid is used as an immunosuppressant drug to prevent graft rejection after transplant. Which of the following enzymes is inhibited by this drug?","answers":[{"option":"Phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate (PRPP) synthetase","bool":false},{"option":"Adenosine deaminase","bool":false},{"option":"Adenylosuccinate synthetase","bool":false},{"option":"Inosine monophosphate (IMP) dehydrogenase","bool":true},{"option":"Dihydrofolate reductase","bool":false}],"id":77},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 32-year-old lady comes to the ultrasound department for an antenatal scan which shows bilateral hydronephrosis, hydro-ureters, and a distended urinary bladder with a keyhole sign in the fetus. The fetus is suspected with a case of posterior urethral valves. She is advised to have a post-natal checkup of the baby. What is the investigation of choice in this particular case?","answers":[{"option":"Kidney, ureter, and bladder (KUB) X-ray","bool":false},{"option":"Voiding cystourethrogram (VCUG)","bool":true},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography scan (CT scan)","bool":false},{"option":"Repeat ultrasound KUB + Prostate","bool":false}],"id":78},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 4-year-old girl presents with severe pitting edema. Further investigations show hypoalbuminemia, lipiduria, and 3.8 g proteinuria. Biopsy confirms the renal disease. Which of the following best describes the pathophysiology of proteinuria in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Tubulointerstitial damage","bool":false},{"option":"Crescent formation in the glomeruli","bool":false},{"option":"Derangement in glomerular capillary walls","bool":true},{"option":"Anti–glomerular basement membrane (anti-GBM) antibodies cross reacting with alveolar basement membranes","bool":false},{"option":"Excess dietary protein intake","bool":false}],"id":79},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy presents with generalized edema and periorbital edema. Further investigations show hypoalbuminemia, lipiduria, and 3.7 g proteinuria. Which of the following conditions is the most likely cause in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Amyloidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":true}],"id":80},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Amina has recently completed her FCPS and now she is pursuing her career as a specialist. She was passionate about this field and always wanted to serve society and live a meaningful life. Which of the following approach of happiness most likely focuses on meaning and self-realization?","answers":[{"option":"Hedonism","bool":false},{"option":"Eudemonia","bool":true},{"option":"Subjective well being","bool":false},{"option":"Psychological well-being","bool":false},{"option":"Happiness","bool":false}],"id":81},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the alkaline nature of the extracellular fluid and acidic urine termed as?","answers":[{"option":"Glucosuria","bool":false},{"option":"Phenyl ketonuria","bool":false},{"option":"Ketonuria","bool":false},{"option":"Amino aciduria","bool":false},{"option":"Paradoxical aciduria","bool":true}],"id":82},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"An adult male had a road traffic accident and went into a hypovolemic shock due to blood loss. Which intravenous fluid is preferable to start as initial available therapy in an emergency?","answers":[{"option":"Haemaccel","bool":true},{"option":"Ringer's lactate","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Amino acid solution","bool":false},{"option":"5% dextrose water","bool":false}],"id":83},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Disturbance in the renal reabsorption of bicarbonates in the proximal tubules leads to which one of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis","bool":true},{"option":"Hypochloremia","bool":false},{"option":"Acidic urine","bool":false},{"option":"Nitrogen retention","bool":false}],"id":84},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"If plasma colloidal osmotic pressure is 40 mmHg, renal capillary pressure is 60 mmHg, and Bowman's capsule hydrostatic pressure is 18 mmHg, which of the following effect occurs in the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) is reduced","bool":true},{"option":"Afferent arteriolar dilatation","bool":false},{"option":"Contraction of macula densa","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) is increased","bool":false},{"option":"Efferent arteriolar dilatation","bool":false}],"id":85},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"In a 60-year-old diabetic patient, a routine lab investigation shows hemoglobin: 8.2 gm/dL, creatinine (Cr): 5.0 mg/dL, calcium (Ca): 6.7 mg/dL, phosphate(PO4): 5.2 mg/dL, with small kidneys on ultrasound. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Acute kidney injury","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary tract infection","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic kidney disease","bool":true},{"option":"Acute interstitial nephritis","bool":false}],"id":86},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"In a patient with severe dehydration, the plasma osmolality increases. This is corrected by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Angiotensin-II","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":false},{"option":"Antidiuretic hormone (ADH)","bool":true},{"option":"Increased intake of glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in protein intake","bool":false}],"id":87},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which one of the following confirms the diagnosis of gout?","answers":[{"option":"Presence of urate crystals in the synovial fluid","bool":true},{"option":"Renal stones","bool":false},{"option":"Redness and pain in joints","bool":false},{"option":"Increased uric acid excretion in urine","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperuricemia","bool":false}],"id":88},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"In purine metabolism, what does the deamination of guanine yield?","answers":[{"option":"Thiamine","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine","bool":true},{"option":"Methyl guanine","bool":false},{"option":"Uracil","bool":false},{"option":"Cytidylic acid","bool":false}],"id":89},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Mr. Mughees did not score well in the exam. He has pessimistic explanatory styles and attributed his failure to generalized bad luck i.e. 'I always had bad luck in all life situations' (stable and global attribution), which lead to him being depressed. Which one of the following could preferably explain the causes of negative events contrary to this pessimistic explanatory style?","answers":[{"option":"Internal, stable","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"External, unstable, specific","bool":false},{"option":"External, global, stable","bool":false},{"option":"Internal, specific, unstable","bool":true}],"id":90},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is carbamoyl phosphate a precursor of?","answers":[{"option":"Uric acid","bool":false},{"option":"Urea","bool":true},{"option":"Hypoxanthine","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine","bool":false},{"option":"Ionosine","bool":false}],"id":91},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What does renal correction of acute hyperkalemia result in?","answers":[{"option":"Increased secretion of H+","bool":false},{"option":"Alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Increased secretion of HCO3-","bool":false},{"option":"Increased secretion of Na+","bool":false},{"option":"Acidosis","bool":true}],"id":92},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following provides arterial supply to the pelvic part of the ureter?","answers":[{"option":"Gonadal artery","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior vesical artery","bool":false},{"option":"Abdominal aorta","bool":false},{"option":"Internal iliac artery","bool":true},{"option":"Renal artery","bool":false}],"id":93},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following do the afferent arterioles arise from?","answers":[{"option":"Peritubular capillaries","bool":false},{"option":"Intralobar artery","bool":false},{"option":"Interlobar artery","bool":false},{"option":"Arcuate artery","bool":false},{"option":"Interlobular artery","bool":true}],"id":94},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the end product of purine metabolism in humans?","answers":[{"option":"Xanthine","bool":false},{"option":"Uric acid","bool":true},{"option":"Hypoxanthine","bool":false},{"option":"Urea","bool":false},{"option":"Inositol","bool":false}],"id":95},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"The examination of a cross-section of kidneys shows the renal columns of Bertin. Which statement best defines the renal columns of Bertin?","answers":[{"option":"Medullary substance that extends into cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Cortical substance that extends into medulla","bool":true},{"option":"Nephrons that are drained by a common collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Convoluted parts of renal tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Marks beginning of nephron","bool":false}],"id":96},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"The substance is freely filtered at the glomerular capillaries but is not excreted into the urine because all the filtered substance is reabsorbed from the tubules back into the blood. This pattern occurs for which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Electrolytes","bool":false},{"option":"Bases","bool":false},{"option":"Inulin","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine","bool":false},{"option":"Amino acids and glucose","bool":true}],"id":97},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"This substance is freely filtered at the glomerular capillaries and is not reabsorbed, but additional quantities of this substance are secreted from the peritubular capillary blood into the renal tubules. Which substance is this?","answers":[{"option":"Organic acids and bases","bool":false},{"option":"Electrolytes","bool":false},{"option":"Amino acids and glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine","bool":true},{"option":"Inulin","bool":false}],"id":98},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"This substance is freely filtered by the glomerular capillaries but is neither reabsorbed nor secreted. Therefore, its excretion rate is equal to the rate at which it was filtered. Which substance is this?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Electrolytes","bool":false},{"option":"Inulin","bool":true},{"option":"Creatinine","bool":false},{"option":"Amino acids","bool":false}],"id":99},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the correct sequence of branching pattern of renal arteries?","answers":[{"option":"Segmental artery > lobar artery > intralobular artery > arcuate artery","bool":false},{"option":"Lobar artery > segmental artery > intralobular artery > arcuate artery","bool":false},{"option":"Segmental artery > interlobar artery > lobar artery > arcuate artery","bool":false},{"option":"Segmental artery > lobar artery > interlobar artery > arcuate artery","bool":true},{"option":"Lobar artery > segmental artery > interlobar artery > arcuate artery","bool":false}],"id":100},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is not the part of renal filtration barrier?","answers":[{"option":"Basal lamina","bool":false},{"option":"Continuous epithelium of glomerular capillaries","bool":true},{"option":"Fenestrated endothelium of glomerular capillaries","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Podocytes","bool":false}],"id":101},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following forms the outermost layer of the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Perinephric fat","bool":false},{"option":"Renal fascia","bool":true},{"option":"Peritoneum","bool":false},{"option":"Only fat","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrous capsule","bool":false}],"id":102},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"What may the kidneys enhance in response to acidosis?","answers":[{"option":"Secretion of HCO₃⁻","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of K⁺ ions","bool":false},{"option":"Urea retention","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of H⁺ ions","bool":true},{"option":"Secretion of Na⁺ ions","bool":false}],"id":103},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Allopurinol is a structural analog of which of the following compounds?","answers":[{"option":"Hypoxanthine","bool":true},{"option":"Phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Inosine monophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Uric acid","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine oxidase","bool":false}],"id":104},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"What is the osmolarity of the glomerular filtrate that enters the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"400 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"100 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"200 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"300 mOsm/L","bool":true},{"option":"1200 mOsm/L","bool":false}],"id":105},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Increased secretion of aldosterone leads to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Hyponatremia","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperkalemia","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis","bool":true},{"option":"Hypernatremia","bool":false}],"id":106},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A female comes into the clinic with oral ulcers, hematuria, and +1 proteinuria. 1-2 white blood cells/HPF are found on urinalysis. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Lupus nephritis","bool":true},{"option":"Glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Acid excretion","bool":false},{"option":"Membranous nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false}],"id":107},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the narrowest part of the ureter, well above the urinary bladder, where stones can get lodged?","answers":[{"option":"Bladder wall","bool":false},{"option":"Major calyx","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvicalyceal junction","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic brim","bool":true},{"option":"Minor calyx","bool":false}],"id":108},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the correct order of the coverings of the kidneys from outwards to inwards?","answers":[{"option":"Renal fascia - Perinephric fat - Paranephric fat - Renal capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Renal capsule - Renal fascia - Perinephric fat - Paranephric fat","bool":false},{"option":"Paranephric fat - Renal fascia - Perinephric fat - Renal capsule","bool":true},{"option":"Renal capsule - Paranephric fat - Perinephric fat - Renal fascia","bool":false},{"option":"Perinephric fat - Renal fascia - Paranephric fat - Renal capsule","bool":false}],"id":109},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy presents to the outpatient clinic with generalized edema and periorbital edema. Blood tests and urine analysis reveal hypoalbuminemia, lipiduria, and 3.7 g proteinuria. A renal biopsy is performed. Which of the following electron microscopic features is most likely to be present in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Crescent shaped glomeruli","bool":false},{"option":"Subepithelial deposits","bool":false},{"option":"Subendothelial deposits","bool":false},{"option":"Thick glomerular basement membrane with immune complex deposition","bool":false},{"option":"Effacement of foot process but no deposits","bool":true}],"id":110},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"How many moles of sodium chloride are there in 0.9% solution?","answers":[{"option":"0.07 moles/L","bool":false},{"option":"0.154 moles/L","bool":true},{"option":"0.123 moles/L","bool":false},{"option":"0.157 moles/L","bool":false},{"option":"0.678 moles/L","bool":false}],"id":111},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What is the width of the filtration slit pores?","answers":[{"option":"15 nm","bool":false},{"option":"20 nm","bool":false},{"option":"24 nm","bool":false},{"option":"25 nm","bool":true},{"option":"13 nm","bool":false}],"id":112},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following parts of the nephron contains urinary space?","answers":[{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":true},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":113},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following arteries does not supply the ureter?","answers":[{"option":"Superior vesical artery","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior mesenteric artery","bool":true},{"option":"Renal artery","bool":false},{"option":"Gonadal artery","bool":false},{"option":"Common iliac artery","bool":false}],"id":114},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following decreases renal plasma flow?","answers":[{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":false},{"option":"Angiotensin I","bool":false},{"option":"Renal hypertension","bool":true},{"option":"Prostaglandin","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":115},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which nerve supplies the external urethral sphincter?","answers":[{"option":"Obturator nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Vesicular nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Gonadal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Femoral nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Pudendal nerve","bool":true}],"id":116},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which part of the nephron is impermeable to sodium chloride (NaCl)?","answers":[{"option":"Descending limb","bool":true},{"option":"Ascending limb","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":117},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"In which part of the nephron does maximum water reabsorption occur?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Collecting tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":118},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which nerve supplies detrusor muscle?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Pudendal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Hypogastric nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar plexus","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic splanchnic nerve","bool":true}],"id":119},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What is autoregulated by macula densa?","answers":[{"option":"Renin release","bool":false},{"option":"Water regulation","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium chloride delivery","bool":false},{"option":"Amino acid absorption","bool":false},{"option":"GFR and renal blood flow","bool":true}],"id":120},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following has transitional epithelium along with mucus glands in the submucosa?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary bladder","bool":true},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":121},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is involved in lymphatic drainage of the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Common iliac node","bool":false},{"option":"Celiac node","bool":false},{"option":"Para-aortic node","bool":true},{"option":"External iliac node","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":122},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Kidneys lie at which vertebrae level?","answers":[{"option":"T4-T12","bool":false},{"option":"L5-S3","bool":false},{"option":"T12-L3","bool":true},{"option":"L4-L5","bool":false},{"option":"S3-S5","bool":false}],"id":123},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following maintains the hyperosmolarity of the renal medulla?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Peritubular capillaries","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Renal artery","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":true}],"id":124},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is the benefit of the salvage pathway?","answers":[{"option":"Increases synthesis of nucleotides","bool":false},{"option":"Provides continous supply of nucleic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Increases the production of nucleic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Increases degradation of nucleotides","bool":false},{"option":"Provides continuous supply of nucleotides","bool":true}],"id":125},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What is the ribose sugar donor in adenine phosphoribosyltransferase?","answers":[{"option":"Carbon dioxide","bool":false},{"option":"Hexose monophosphate shunt","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphoribosyl diphosphate (PRPP)","bool":true},{"option":"Adenosine","bool":false},{"option":"Dihydrofolate","bool":false}],"id":126},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Inosine monophosphate leads to the formation of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Adenine monophosphate and cytosine monophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Cytosine monophosphate and thymine monophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Thymine monophosphate and adenine monophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Guanine monophosphate and adenine monophosphate","bool":true},{"option":"Cytosine monophosphate and guanine monophosphate","bool":false}],"id":127},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is correct for osmolarity?","answers":[{"option":"Moles per kg of solution","bool":false},{"option":"Grams per liter of solution","bool":false},{"option":"Moles per liter of solution","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Liter per moles of solution","bool":false}],"id":128},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"A high concentration of antidiuretic hormone can cause how much osmolarity of the urine?","answers":[{"option":"200 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"600 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"1200 mOsm/L","bool":true},{"option":"100 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"400 mOsm/L","bool":false}],"id":129},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What is the site of obstruction of ureter that can cause hydronephrosis?","answers":[{"option":"Pelviureteric junction","bool":false},{"option":"Site of attachment with bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic brim","bool":false},{"option":"Ureterovesical junction","bool":false},{"option":"All of these","bool":true}],"id":130},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What makes water a universal solvent?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Having strong hydrogen bonds","bool":false},{"option":"Ability to dissolve many solutes","bool":true},{"option":"Taking any shape","bool":false},{"option":"Ability to split into ions","bool":false}],"id":131},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for water reabsorption under antidiuretic hormone?","answers":[{"option":"Distal tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Descending limb","bool":false},{"option":"Ascending limb","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":true},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":132},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"In which of the following conditions coarse, discrete corticomedullary scars overlying blunted calyces along with flattened papillae are found?","answers":[{"option":"Hydronephrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic pyelonephritis","bool":true},{"option":"Cystitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute pyelonephritis","bool":false}],"id":133},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following can not occur in mixed acid-base disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Respiratory alkalosis and metabolic acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Anion-gap acidosis and non-anion gap acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory acidosis and respiratory alkalosis","bool":true},{"option":"All of these","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis and respiratory acidosis","bool":false}],"id":134},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following does not affect potassium excretion?","answers":[{"option":"Antidiuretic hormone","bool":true},{"option":"Angiotensin","bool":false},{"option":"Intracellular concentration of potassium","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":false},{"option":"Insulin","bool":false}],"id":135},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"A 6-year-old boy is brought to the emergency by his parents with swelling around the eyes, puffiness, and lethargy. His urine examination shows selective proteinuria with no presence of casts and blood. He improves with steroid therapy. What is the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Membranous nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":true},{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":false}],"id":136},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Thiazide diuretics act on which part of the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Thick ascending limb","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":137},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect for staghorn calculi?","answers":[{"option":"Occupies pelvis and one calyx","bool":true},{"option":"Can have hematuria","bool":false},{"option":"Has flank pain","bool":false},{"option":"Presents with infection","bool":false},{"option":"Comprises of magnesium ammonium phosphate","bool":false}],"id":138},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"The contents of the renal hilum from anterior to posterior are:","answers":[{"option":"Renal artery, renal pelvis, renal vein","bool":false},{"option":"Renal artery, renal vein, renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal vein, para-aortic nodes, renal artery, renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal vein, renal artery, renal pelvis","bool":true},{"option":"Renal pelvis, renal vein, renal artery","bool":false}],"id":139},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What is the effect of sympathetic stimulation on kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"Decreases water reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Decreases GFR","bool":true},{"option":"Decreases NaCl reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Increases GFR","bool":false},{"option":"Increases renal blood flow","bool":false}],"id":140},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Through which of the following actions, allopurinol decreases the production of uric acid?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of gene responsible for the formation of xanthine oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Competitive inhibition of xanthine oxidase","bool":true},{"option":"Decrease substrate availability of xanthine oxidase","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in xanthine oxidase production","bool":false},{"option":"Allosteric inhibition of xanthine oxidase","bool":false}],"id":141},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"How does distal convoluted tubule (DCT) different from proximal convoluted tubule (PCT)?","answers":[{"option":"DCT cells does not have prominent brush border","bool":true},{"option":"DCT cells stain dark pink","bool":false},{"option":"DCT cells have more mitochondria","bool":false},{"option":"DCT cells give impression of less nuclei","bool":false},{"option":"DCT cells are taller","bool":false}],"id":142},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following structure is responsible for holding the kidney in its place?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic fat","bool":false},{"option":"Perinephric fat","bool":true},{"option":"Renal capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Pararenal fat","bool":false}],"id":143},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is a cause of intrinsic renal failure?","answers":[{"option":"Bilateral renal stenosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Diarrhea","bool":false},{"option":"Benign prostatic hyperplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Renal stone","bool":false}],"id":144},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common radiopaque stone?","answers":[{"option":"Calcium phosphate stone","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium oxalate stone","bool":true},{"option":"Struvite stone","bool":false},{"option":"Uric acid stone","bool":false},{"option":"Cystine stone","bool":false}],"id":145},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common radiolucent stone seen?","answers":[{"option":"Cystine stone","bool":false},{"option":"Uric acid stone","bool":true},{"option":"Calcium phosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium oxalate","bool":false},{"option":"Ammonium magnesium phosphate","bool":false}],"id":146},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following diuretics causes hyperkalemia?","answers":[{"option":"Furosemide","bool":false},{"option":"Chlorothiazide","bool":false},{"option":"Bumetanide","bool":false},{"option":"Trichlormethiazide","bool":false},{"option":"Spironolactone","bool":true}],"id":147},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"How much uric acid is normally excreted each day in urine?","answers":[{"option":"1-100 mg","bool":false},{"option":"100-200 mg","bool":false},{"option":"1000-1200 mg","bool":false},{"option":"250-750 mg","bool":true},{"option":"800-1000 mg","bool":false}],"id":148},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is not present in nephrotic syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Hyperlipidemia","bool":false},{"option":"Proteinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoalbuminuria","bool":true},{"option":"Edema","bool":false}],"id":149},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What is the cause of the high osmolality of urine?","answers":[{"option":"Non-functioning adrenal gland","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes insipidus","bool":false},{"option":"Oversecretion of antidiuretic hormone","bool":true},{"option":"Low sodium","bool":false},{"option":"High water intake","bool":false}],"id":150},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is required for the creatinine clearance test?","answers":[{"option":"12 hours urine","bool":false},{"option":"24 hours urine and serum","bool":true},{"option":"6 hours urine and serum","bool":false},{"option":"6 hours urine","bool":false},{"option":"24 hours urine","bool":false}],"id":151},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What will be the pH of hydrogen ions having the concentration of 0.0004?","answers":[{"option":"4.0","bool":false},{"option":"6.7","bool":false},{"option":"1.2","bool":false},{"option":"3.4","bool":true},{"option":"6.5","bool":false}],"id":152},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following buffers best maintain the physiological pH?","answers":[{"option":"Phosphate buffer","bool":false},{"option":"Protein buffer","bool":false},{"option":"Chloride buffer","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrogen buffer","bool":false},{"option":"Bicarbonate buffer","bool":true}],"id":153},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"At what point of urination should the urine be collected for urine sampling?","answers":[{"option":"From the start till the end","bool":false},{"option":"Mid-stream urine","bool":true},{"option":"End urine","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Start urine","bool":false}],"id":154},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following enzymes is used to convert hypoxanthine to xanthine?","answers":[{"option":"Xanthine synthase","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine dehydrogenase","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine hydrogenase","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine oxidase","bool":true}],"id":155},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is required in the conversion of inosine monophosphate to adenosine monophosphate?","answers":[{"option":"Glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Water","bool":false},{"option":"Aspartate","bool":true},{"option":"Carbon dioxide","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamate","bool":false}],"id":156},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Nitrite in urine indicates which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Urinary tract infection","bool":true},{"option":"Viral infection","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney stones","bool":false},{"option":"Hydronephrosis","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":157},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following enzymes is deficient in Lesch Nyan syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Inosine monophosphate dehydrogenase","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyltransferase (HGPRT) enzyme","bool":true},{"option":"Guanine monophosphate synthase","bool":false},{"option":"Xanthine oxidase","bool":false}],"id":158},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which test is used to detect blood in urine?","answers":[{"option":"Emulsion test","bool":false},{"option":"Benzidine test","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Chromatography","bool":false},{"option":"Benedict test","bool":false}],"id":159},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"What is the percentage of water in lean body mass?","answers":[{"option":"60%","bool":true},{"option":"50%","bool":false},{"option":"90%","bool":false},{"option":"70%","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":160},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Increase in which of the following results in the secretion of aldosterone?","answers":[{"option":"Chloride","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrogen","bool":false},{"option":"Water","bool":false},{"option":"Potassium","bool":true},{"option":"Sodium","bool":false}],"id":161},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for the reabsorption of sodium after hemorrhage?","answers":[{"option":"Epinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":true},{"option":"Vasopressin","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Atrial natriuretic peptide","bool":false}],"id":162},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"In response to which condition does the glutaminase activity of the kidney increase?","answers":[{"option":"All of these","bool":false},{"option":"Hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acidosis","bool":true},{"option":"Shock","bool":false}],"id":163},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2016"],"question":"A 27-year-old male presents with a history of altered consciousness for one day. Arterial blood gas (ABG) results show pH 7.1, PCO2 = 16 mmHg, HCO3 = 10 mmol/L and pO2 = 65 mmHg. Which of the following is the most likely condition?","answers":[{"option":"Uncompensated respiratory acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Compensated respiratory alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis","bool":true},{"option":"Renal failure","bool":false}],"id":164},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following options best describes the function of the antidiuretic hormone?","answers":[{"option":"Decreases sodium reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Decreases water reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Increases sodium reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Increases urea secretion","bool":false},{"option":"Increases water reabsorption","bool":true}],"id":165},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"What is the term used for the presence of orotate in the urine?","answers":[{"option":"Orotic aciduria","bool":true},{"option":"Alkaptonuria","bool":false},{"option":"Phenylketonuria","bool":false},{"option":"Maple syrup urine disease","bool":false},{"option":"Homocystinuria","bool":false}],"id":166},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not kidney cystic disease?","answers":[{"option":"Childhood polycystic kidney disease","bool":false},{"option":"Medullary sponge disease","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant tubulointerstitial kidney disease","bool":false},{"option":"Adulthood polycystic kidney disease","bool":false},{"option":"Hydronephrosis","bool":true}],"id":167},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following vessels do the efferent arterioles drain into?","answers":[{"option":"Peritubular capillaries","bool":true},{"option":"Inferior mesenteric vein","bool":false},{"option":"Afferent arteriole","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":false},{"option":"Capillary tuft","bool":false}],"id":168},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following nodes does the kidney drain into?","answers":[{"option":"Pre-aortic nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Para-aortic nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Inguinal nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Thoracic nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Celiac nodes","bool":false}],"id":169},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following organs produces erythropoietin?","answers":[{"option":"Gall bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":true},{"option":"Thymus","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow","bool":false}],"id":170},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following crystal is deposited in gout?","answers":[{"option":"Calcium carbonate crystals","bool":false},{"option":"Monosodium urate monohydrate crystals","bool":true},{"option":"Sodium chloride crystals","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium pyrophosphate crystals","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroxyapatite crystals","bool":false}],"id":171},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"What is the most common abnormality of hemodialysis?","answers":[{"option":"Depression","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotension","bool":true},{"option":"Itching","bool":false},{"option":"Infection","bool":false},{"option":"Amyloidosis","bool":false}],"id":172},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"What is prerenal azotemia caused by?","answers":[{"option":"Renal papillary necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Benign prostatic hyperplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":true},{"option":"Rhabdomyolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Ureteral stones","bool":false}],"id":173},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following statements concerning the three main structures of the hilum of the kidney is incorrect?","answers":[{"option":"The renal veins empty directly into the inferior vena cava","bool":false},{"option":"The anatomy of the contents of the hilum can be variable","bool":false},{"option":"The right renal vein is longer than the left","bool":true},{"option":"The renal pelvis is normally the most posterior of the three","bool":false},{"option":"The renal artery divides into 3-5 segmental arteries at the hilum","bool":false}],"id":174},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Sodium on the basolateral side is absorbed from the late distal convoluted tubules by:","answers":[{"option":"Symport","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium-hydrogen ATPase","bool":false},{"option":"Cotransport","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium-hydrogen antiport","bool":false},{"option":"Active transport","bool":true}],"id":175},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is not seen in chronic renal failure?","answers":[{"option":"Hyperkalemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperprolactinemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Hypocalcemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperphosphatemia","bool":false}],"id":176},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"What is the osmolarity of filtrate?","answers":[{"option":"125 mOsm/l","bool":false},{"option":"300 mOsm/l","bool":true},{"option":"600 mOsm/l","bool":false},{"option":"250 mOsm/l","bool":false},{"option":"30 mOsm/l","bool":false}],"id":177},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"The parallelogram of Morris is used to determine the surface anatomy of which organ?","answers":[{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":true},{"option":"Stomach","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false}],"id":178},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"What is formed from the pelvic part of the urogenital sinus?","answers":[{"option":"Genital tubercle","bool":false},{"option":"Entire urethra in females","bool":true},{"option":"Trigone","bool":false},{"option":"Clitoral primordium","bool":false},{"option":"Base of the bladder","bool":false}],"id":179},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following enzymes is blocked by sulfonamide in prokaroytes?","answers":[{"option":"Peptidyl transferase","bool":false},{"option":"Topoisomerase","bool":false},{"option":"Dihydrofolate reductase","bool":false},{"option":"Amidotransferase","bool":false},{"option":"Dihydropteroate synthase","bool":true}],"id":180},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"What is the normal value of fraction filtration value?","answers":[{"option":"100%","bool":false},{"option":"45%","bool":false},{"option":"60%","bool":false},{"option":"20%","bool":true},{"option":"33%","bool":false}],"id":181},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"If the total body water in a human is 42 L, what would be the volume of the extracellular fluid?","answers":[{"option":"25 L","bool":false},{"option":"10 L","bool":false},{"option":"23 L","bool":false},{"option":"20 L","bool":false},{"option":"14 L","bool":true}],"id":182},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which one of the following options is the best opposing factor to glomerular filtration?","answers":[{"option":"Peritubular capillary hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's capsule colloid osmotic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular capillary colloid osmotic pressure","bool":true},{"option":"Bowman's capsule hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular capillary hydrostatic pressure","bool":false}],"id":183},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which one of the following is not used to measure glomerular filtration rate?","answers":[{"option":"Inulin","bool":false},{"option":"Cystatin C","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine","bool":false},{"option":"Urea","bool":true},{"option":"Iothalamate","bool":false}],"id":184},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following acts as a selective barrier?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular basement membrane","bool":true}],"id":185},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following causes hypernatremia?","answers":[{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false},{"option":"Diarrhea","bool":false},{"option":"Renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes insipidus","bool":true},{"option":"Coma","bool":false}],"id":186},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which structure is not considered a part of the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Medullary collecting ducts","bool":true},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false},{"option":"Mesangial cells","bool":false}],"id":187},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is seen in nephritic syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Edema","bool":false},{"option":"Proteinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoalbuniemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hematuria","bool":true},{"option":"Lipiduria","bool":false}],"id":188},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"In order for a patient to be connected to a dialysis machine, what must occur?","answers":[{"option":"Creation of arteriovenous fistula","bool":true},{"option":"Creation of ventriculoatrial shunt","bool":false},{"option":"Creation of lumboperitoneal shunt","bool":false},{"option":"Creation of ventriculoperitoneal shunt","bool":false},{"option":"Creation of ventriculogallbladder shunt","bool":false}],"id":189},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following will be a complication of chronic renal failure?","answers":[{"option":"Hypernatremia","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":true},{"option":"Polyuria","bool":false},{"option":"Hypokalemia","bool":false}],"id":190},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following drugs can cause hyperkalemia?","answers":[{"option":"Thiazides","bool":false},{"option":"Acetazolamide","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrocortisone","bool":false},{"option":"Furosemide","bool":false},{"option":"Spironolactone","bool":true}],"id":191},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2017"],"question":"Which of the following does not increase serum creatinine levels?","answers":[{"option":"Intense exercise","bool":false},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":false},{"option":"Dialysis","bool":true},{"option":"Shock","bool":false},{"option":"Congestive heart failure","bool":false}],"id":192},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the percentage of water in the urine?","answers":[{"option":"99%","bool":false},{"option":"80%","bool":false},{"option":"95%","bool":true},{"option":"85%","bool":false},{"option":"75%","bool":false}],"id":193},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following will lead to a reduction in glomerular filtration rate (GFR)?","answers":[{"option":"Reduction in glomerular capillary colloid osmotic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Reduction in Bowman's capsule hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Reduction in peritubular capillary hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Reduction in glomerular capillary hydrostatic pressure","bool":true},{"option":"Increase in Bowman's capsule colloid osmotic pressure","bool":false}],"id":194},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"The urinary space is present between which of the following layers?","answers":[{"option":"Parietal layer and visceral layer","bool":true},{"option":"Endothelial layer and visceral layer","bool":false},{"option":"Parietal layer and basement membrane","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelial layer and parietal layer","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelial layer and basement membrane","bool":false}],"id":195},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"In a hematoxylin and eosin (H&E) stained section, which type of epithelium would a part of the nephron, present adjacent to the glomerulus in the cortex, have?","answers":[{"option":"Simple squamous","bool":false},{"option":"Simple cuboidal","bool":true},{"option":"Pseudostratified","bool":false},{"option":"Transitional","bool":false},{"option":"Stratified columnar","bool":false}],"id":196},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"When the urine is fully concentrated, what is the osmolality relative to that of blood plasma?","answers":[{"option":"10-11 times more","bool":false},{"option":"8-9 times more","bool":false},{"option":"4-5 times more","bool":true},{"option":"2-3 times more","bool":false},{"option":"6-7 times more","bool":false}],"id":197},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following causes of lactic acidosis is most common?","answers":[{"option":"Pyruvate dehydrogenase complex (PDC) deficiency disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Excessive exercise","bool":false},{"option":"Liver disease","bool":false},{"option":"Malignancy","bool":false},{"option":"Septic shock","bool":true}],"id":198},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following investigations is used routinely for benign prostatic hyperplasia (BPH)?","answers":[{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous pyelography","bool":false},{"option":"X-ray","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound","bool":true},{"option":"Computerized tomography (CT)","bool":false}],"id":199},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which condition results in thyroidization of kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"Acute cystitis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic cystitis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic pyelonephritis","bool":true},{"option":"Tubulointerstitial nephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute pyelonephritis","bool":false}],"id":200},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the characteristic finding of minimal change disease (MCD)?","answers":[{"option":"Crescent-shapes seen in the Bowman space of glomeruli","bool":false},{"option":"Thickened glomerular membranes with a \"tram-track\" appearance","bool":false},{"option":"Normal basement membrane with podocyte effacement","bool":true},{"option":"Sclerosis of particular segments of some glomeruli","bool":false},{"option":"Thickened glomerular membranes with \"spike and dome\" epithelial deposits","bool":false}],"id":201},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the rate-limiting step in pyrimidine synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Formation of phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate (PRPP)","bool":false},{"option":"Formation of orotate","bool":false},{"option":"Formation of carbamoyl phosphate-2","bool":true},{"option":"Formation of carbamoyl phosphate-1","bool":false},{"option":"Formation of carbamoylaspartate","bool":false}],"id":202},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following organs stores urine, and has ligamentous connections at the neck?","answers":[{"option":"Ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Urethra","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder","bool":true},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pelvis","bool":false}],"id":203},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the normal specific gravity of urine in adults?","answers":[{"option":"1.050-1.070","bool":false},{"option":"1.030-1.050","bool":false},{"option":"1.070-1.090","bool":false},{"option":"1.010-1.030","bool":true},{"option":"1.090-1.110","bool":false}],"id":204},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which glucose transporter is present on the luminal side in the early part of the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"SGLT-1","bool":false},{"option":"SGLT-2","bool":true},{"option":"GLUT-2","bool":false},{"option":"GLUT-4","bool":false},{"option":"GLUT-1","bool":false}],"id":205},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the amount of proteinuria in minimal change disease?","answers":[{"option":"Greater than 10 g","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 3.5 g","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 10 g","bool":false},{"option":"Greater than 3.5 g","bool":true},{"option":"No proteinuria","bool":false}],"id":206},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"In pyrimidine catabolism, what does the deamination of cytosine yield?","answers":[{"option":"Thiamine","bool":false},{"option":"Cytidylate","bool":false},{"option":"Cytidylic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Uracil","bool":true},{"option":"Methyl cytosine","bool":false}],"id":207},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Glucose co-transporter is found at which part of the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Ascending limb","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Descending limb","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":true}],"id":208},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following may result in metabolic alkalosis?","answers":[{"option":"Carbon monoxide poisoning","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperventilation","bool":false},{"option":"Diarrhea","bool":false},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":true},{"option":"Type 1 diabetes mellitus","bool":false}],"id":209},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for the sterility of the genitourinary tract?","answers":[{"option":"B cells","bool":false},{"option":"T cells","bool":false},{"option":"IgA","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary flow","bool":true},{"option":"Low pH","bool":false}],"id":210},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following contraindications of urinary catheterization should be ruled out before performing the procedure?","answers":[{"option":"Urethral infection","bool":false},{"option":"Urethral strictures","bool":true},{"option":"Urinary incontinence","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Patient refusal","bool":false}],"id":211},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following shows a bright shadow in ultrasound?","answers":[{"option":"Fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Fat","bool":false},{"option":"Cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Calculus","bool":true}],"id":212},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the function of the juxtaglomerular apparatus?","answers":[{"option":"Angiotensin secretion to reduce blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Renin secretion to reduce blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Renin secretion to increase blood pressure","bool":true},{"option":"Angiotensin secretion to increase blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Angiotensinogen secretion","bool":false}],"id":213},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which part of the nephron contains Na/glucose transporters?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":214},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"H+ ion secretion in proximal convoluted tubule is done by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Na+/H+ exchanger","bool":true},{"option":"Glucose/H+ exchanger","bool":false},{"option":"Cl-/H+ exchanger","bool":false},{"option":"K+/H+ exchanger","bool":false},{"option":"All of these","bool":false}],"id":215},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"The least distensible part of the urinary bladder arises from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Phallic part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Allantois","bool":false},{"option":"Mesonephric duct","bool":true},{"option":"Vesical part of urogenital sinus","bool":false}],"id":216},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the most common causative agent of continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) peritonitis?","answers":[{"option":"Staphylococcus saprophyticus","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus mirabilis","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Pseudomonas aeroginosa","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus epidermidis","bool":true}],"id":217},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is an indication for dialysis?","answers":[{"option":"Hypokalemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypernatremia","bool":false},{"option":"GFR < 50%","bool":false},{"option":"Hypovolemia","bool":false},{"option":"GFR < 15%","bool":true}],"id":218},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Glomerular filtration depends upon the renal blood flow. To achieve the normal glomerular filtration rate (GFR) of 180 L/day, what would the fraction of renal plasma flow that is filtered average?","answers":[{"option":"5%","bool":false},{"option":"10%","bool":false},{"option":"20%","bool":true},{"option":"40%","bool":false},{"option":"30%","bool":false}],"id":219},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is associated with a sudden loss of hearing?","answers":[{"option":"Bumetanide","bool":false},{"option":"Furosemide","bool":true},{"option":"Torsemide","bool":false},{"option":"Ethacrynic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Azathioprine","bool":false}],"id":220},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is effective in mountain sickness?","answers":[{"option":"Acetazolamide","bool":true},{"option":"Bumetanide","bool":false},{"option":"Torsemide","bool":false},{"option":"Furosemide","bool":false},{"option":"Ethacrynic acid","bool":false}],"id":221},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"The production of pyruvate from phosphoenolpyruvate (PEP) is an example of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Isomerization","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphorylation","bool":false},{"option":"Oxidative phosphorylation","bool":false},{"option":"Aldol condensation","bool":false},{"option":"Substrate level phosphorylation","bool":true}],"id":222},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following refers to the most common position of the appendix?","answers":[{"option":"Rectovesicular","bool":false},{"option":"Rectosigmoid","bool":false},{"option":"Retrocecal","bool":true},{"option":"Transverse","bool":false},{"option":"Rectouterine","bool":false}],"id":223},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"The epithelium of the esophagus has which of the following functions?","answers":[{"option":"Absorptive only","bool":false},{"option":"Protective and absorptive","bool":false},{"option":"Protective and secretory","bool":true},{"option":"Secretory only","bool":false},{"option":"Protective only","bool":false}],"id":224},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is involved both in glycolysis and gluconeogenesis?","answers":[{"option":"Phosphofructokinase-2","bool":false},{"option":"Hexokinase","bool":false},{"option":"Pyruvate kinase","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphofructokinase-1","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphoglycerate kinase","bool":true}],"id":225},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is the fraction filtration formula?","answers":[{"option":"Renal blood flow (RBF) divided by glomerular filtration rate (GFR)","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic blood pressure divided by glomerular filtration rate (GFR)","bool":false},{"option":"Renal plasma flow (RPF) divided by glomerular filtration rate (GFR)","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular filtration rate (GFR) divided by renal plasma flow (RPF)","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":226},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is the function of a kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Reabsorbs sulfuric acid and phosphoric acid","bool":false},{"option":"Produces erythrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Produces the active form of vitamin D","bool":true},{"option":"Activates vitamin K","bool":false},{"option":"Performs glucuronidation","bool":false}],"id":227},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Discern which of the following are the functions of the kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"Only long-term blood pressure regulation, and blood acid-base balance","bool":false},{"option":"Short and long-term blood pressure regulation only","bool":false},{"option":"Blood acid-base balance only","bool":false},{"option":"Only short-term blood pressure regulation, and blood acid-base balance","bool":false},{"option":"Short and long-term blood pressure regulation, and blood acid-base balance","bool":true}],"id":228},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following blood vessels are involved in the counter-current exchange?","answers":[{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":true},{"option":"Vasa nervosum","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa vasorum","bool":false},{"option":"Varicose veins","bool":false},{"option":"Vinae comitantes","bool":false}],"id":229},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is a tool for the classification of acute kidney injury?","answers":[{"option":"RIFLE criteria","bool":true},{"option":"HHELPSS","bool":false},{"option":"JONES criteria","bool":false},{"option":"GUN criteria","bool":false},{"option":"HACEK","bool":false}],"id":230},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Aspartate and glutamine are used in the production of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Triglyceride","bool":false},{"option":"Ribose","bool":false},{"option":"Purine","bool":true},{"option":"Glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Cholesterol","bool":false}],"id":231},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What are nephrons?","answers":[{"option":"Structural and functional units of brains","bool":false},{"option":"Structural and functional units of heart","bool":false},{"option":"Structural and functional units of kidneys","bool":true},{"option":"Structural and functional units of spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Structural and functional units of liver","bool":false}],"id":232},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is the lower limit of the tubular fluid pH in collecting ducts?","answers":[{"option":"3.5","bool":false},{"option":"5.5","bool":false},{"option":"2.5","bool":false},{"option":"4.5","bool":true},{"option":"1.5","bool":false}],"id":233},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of these does not supply blood to the ureter?","answers":[{"option":"Inferior mesenteric artery","bool":true},{"option":"Umbilical artery","bool":false},{"option":"Superior vesical artery","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior vesical artery","bool":false},{"option":"Internal iliac artery","bool":false}],"id":234},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"When calculating the obligatory urine volume of a 70 kg man, what would be the maximal concentrating ability of the kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"1,200 mOsm/L","bool":true},{"option":"0.5 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"600 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"10,000 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"70 mOsm/L","bool":false}],"id":235},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"H+ and K+ are mainly secreted in what section of the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":true},{"option":"Descending loop","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Ascending loop","bool":false}],"id":236},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What does the pelvic part of the urogenital sinus form?","answers":[{"option":"Vagina","bool":false},{"option":"Urethra","bool":true},{"option":"Fallopian tubes","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Kidneys","bool":false}],"id":237},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding acute kidney injury?","answers":[{"option":"Often reversible","bool":true},{"option":"Requires transplantation","bool":false},{"option":"Is irreversible","bool":false},{"option":"Due to severe progressive scarring in kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Requires dialysis","bool":false}],"id":238},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is the outermost layer of the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Renal fascia","bool":true},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Perinephric fat","bool":false}],"id":239},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding hemodialysis?","answers":[{"option":"Used to help restore erythropoietin levels","bool":false},{"option":"Used to help restore body fluid and electrolyte balances","bool":true},{"option":"Used to help restore kidney function","bool":false},{"option":"Used to help restore erythrocyte numbers","bool":false},{"option":"Used to help restore gluconeogenesis","bool":false}],"id":240},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the order of the structures surrounding the kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"Capsule → perinephric fat → renal fascia → paranephric fat","bool":true},{"option":"Paranephric fat → perinephric fat → renal fascia → capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Capsule → paranephric fat → renal fascia → perinephric fat","bool":false},{"option":"Perinephric fat → renal fascia → paranephric fat → capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Capsule → paranephric fat → perinephric fat → renal fascia","bool":false}],"id":241},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following blood vessels stops the ascent of the horseshoe kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Renal vein","bool":false},{"option":"Renal artery","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior mesenteric artery","bool":true},{"option":"Superior mesenteric artery","bool":false},{"option":"Celiac trunk","bool":false}],"id":242},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"A patient arrived at the clinic with complaints of no urine production. The attending physician ran a CT scan to identify the underlying cause. The scan showed an enlarged bladder and hydronephrosis. Which of the following could be a possible cause for this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Kidney failure","bool":false},{"option":"Obstruction at urethra","bool":true},{"option":"Obstruction at ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Unilateral kidney stone at pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Gardnerella vaginalis infection","bool":false}],"id":243},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Under the same conditions, why is the rate of flow of honey lower compared to water?","answers":[{"option":"Water has less calories","bool":false},{"option":"Honey is less heavy per unit volume","bool":false},{"option":"Water has a lower boiling point","bool":false},{"option":"Honey has a higher viscosity","bool":true},{"option":"Honey has a lower density","bool":false}],"id":244},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Extracellular fluid osmolarity increases in which state?","answers":[{"option":"Edema","bool":false},{"option":"Lack of salt consumption","bool":false},{"option":"Excess hydration","bool":false},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":true},{"option":"Excess salt excretion","bool":false}],"id":245},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Up to how many hours post-intercourse is an intra-uterine contraceptive device most effective?","answers":[{"option":"120 hours","bool":true},{"option":"2 hours","bool":false},{"option":"60 minutes","bool":false},{"option":"150 minutes","bool":false},{"option":"3 hours","bool":false}],"id":246},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What percentage of sodium is reabsorbed in the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"100%","bool":false},{"option":"20%","bool":false},{"option":"65%","bool":true},{"option":"40%","bool":false},{"option":"80%","bool":false}],"id":247},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is primarily hereditary?","answers":[{"option":"Alport syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":false},{"option":"Rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis","bool":false}],"id":248},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Upon respiratory acidosis, how does the body compensate for the change in pH?","answers":[{"option":"Increase in HCO₃⁻ reabsorption","bool":true},{"option":"Decrease in H⁺ excretion","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperventilation","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease in HCO₃⁻ reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoventilation","bool":false}],"id":249},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What do the antibodies in Goodpasture syndrome target?","answers":[{"option":"Protein in basement membranes of glomeruli","bool":true},{"option":"Acetylcholine receptor","bool":false},{"option":"Platelet membrane proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cell membrane proteins","bool":false},{"option":"Thyroid-stimulating hormone receptor","bool":false}],"id":250},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the mucosa of the bladder lined by?","answers":[{"option":"Adventitia","bool":false},{"option":"Serosa","bool":false},{"option":"Urothelium","bool":true},{"option":"Endothelium","bool":false},{"option":"Renal fascia","bool":false}],"id":251},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the function of the detrusor muscle?","answers":[{"option":"Opens urethral lumen","bool":false},{"option":"Helps fill up the bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Empties renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Blocks urethral lumen","bool":false},{"option":"Contracts to empty the bladder","bool":true}],"id":252},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Where do the tip of pyramids open at?","answers":[{"option":"Capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Minor calyx","bool":true},{"option":"Cortex","bool":false}],"id":253},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following primarily secretes renin?","answers":[{"option":"Hepatocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Principal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Juxtaglomerular cells","bool":true},{"option":"Alveoli","bool":false},{"option":"Intercalated cells","bool":false}],"id":254},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following decreases H⁺ secretion?","answers":[{"option":"Increased HCO₃⁻ absorption","bool":false},{"option":"Increased pCO₂","bool":false},{"option":"Ammonia synthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoventilation","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased HCO₃⁻ absorption","bool":true}],"id":255},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following structures is present in front of transverse processes?","answers":[{"option":"Esophagus","bool":false},{"option":"Rectum","bool":false},{"option":"Aorta","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter","bool":true}],"id":256},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not required for catheterization?","answers":[{"option":"Urine drainage bag","bool":false},{"option":"Distilled water","bool":false},{"option":"Foley tube","bool":false},{"option":"Dettol","bool":true},{"option":"Lidocaine","bool":false}],"id":257},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is created by a physician for a patient who undergoes chronic dialysis?","answers":[{"option":"Portal vein","bool":false},{"option":"Foramen ovale","bool":false},{"option":"Arteriolymphatic fistula","bool":false},{"option":"Arteriovenous fistula","bool":true},{"option":"Capillary bed","bool":false}],"id":258},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What is the afferent arteriole a branch of?","answers":[{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false},{"option":"Renal vein","bool":false},{"option":"Interlobular artery","bool":true},{"option":"Efferent arteriole","bool":false}],"id":259},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect regarding the female urethra?","answers":[{"option":"It is approximately 20 cm long","bool":true},{"option":"It is approximately 5 cm long","bool":false},{"option":"It is initially lined with transitional epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"The middle part is surrounded by the external striated muscle sphincter","bool":false},{"option":"The area continuous with the labia majora is lined with non-keratinized stratified squamous epithelium","bool":false}],"id":260},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What urea transporter is present in the thin descending loop of Henle?","answers":[{"option":"UT- B1","bool":false},{"option":"UT- A2","bool":true},{"option":"UT- A3","bool":false},{"option":"UT- A1","bool":false},{"option":"UT- B2","bool":false}],"id":261},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is a counter transporter that aids in Na⁺ reabsorption in the proximal tubule?","answers":[{"option":"Na⁺-glucose transporter","bool":false},{"option":"Na⁺/K⁺/2Cl⁻ transporter","bool":false},{"option":"Na⁺ channel","bool":false},{"option":"Na⁺-H⁺ transporter","bool":true},{"option":"Na⁺-Cl⁻ transporter","bool":false}],"id":262},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following structures is not related to the anterior surface of the right kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Duodenum","bool":false},{"option":"Suprarenal gland","bool":false},{"option":"Pylorus","bool":true},{"option":"Right  colic  flexure","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false}],"id":263},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"At what point of a kidney does the renal artery enter?","answers":[{"option":"Hilum","bool":true},{"option":"Pyramid","bool":false},{"option":"Capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false}],"id":264},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"What material is used for individuals who are allergic to latex catheters?","answers":[{"option":"Silicone","bool":true},{"option":"Cotton","bool":false},{"option":"Plastic","bool":false},{"option":"Rubber","bool":false},{"option":"Metal","bool":false}],"id":265},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"At what part of the gastrointestinal tract does nucleic acid digestion mostly occur?","answers":[{"option":"Esophagus","bool":false},{"option":"Mouth","bool":false},{"option":"Rectum","bool":false},{"option":"Small intestine","bool":true},{"option":"Appendix","bool":false}],"id":266},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is not associated with increased potassium excretion?","answers":[{"option":"Ethacrynic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Mannitol","bool":false},{"option":"Acetazolamide","bool":false},{"option":"Furosemide","bool":false},{"option":"Sprionolactone","bool":true}],"id":267},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for xanthogranulomatous pyelonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Proteus","bool":true},{"option":"Salmonella","bool":false},{"option":"Neisseria gonorrhoeae","bool":false},{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false},{"option":"Klebsiella","bool":false}],"id":268},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for the autonomous parasympathetic regulation of the bladder?","answers":[{"option":"Pelvic splanchnic nerve","bool":true},{"option":"Cervical plexus","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar splanchnic nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar plexus","bool":false}],"id":269},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following drugs are responsible for impairing kidney function?","answers":[{"option":"NSAIDs and angiotensin-I converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors","bool":true},{"option":"Penicillin","bool":false},{"option":"Antacids","bool":false},{"option":"Thiazides","bool":false},{"option":"Loop diuretics","bool":false}],"id":270},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Both the ureter and urinary bladder have which type of nerve supply?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Parasympathetic only","bool":false},{"option":"Sympathetic only","bool":false},{"option":"Preganglionic fibers","bool":false},{"option":"Parasympathetic and sympathetic","bool":true}],"id":271},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not present at the posterior of the bladder?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Uterus","bool":false},{"option":"Rectovesical pouch","bool":false},{"option":"Rectum","bool":false},{"option":"Retropubic space","bool":true}],"id":272},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which one of these pathologic features and disease combinations is correct?","answers":[{"option":"Thyroidization - chronic pyelonephritis","bool":true},{"option":"Chicken wire loop pattern of glomerular capillaries - IgA nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophilic infiltrate in the interstitium - hydronephrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Nodular glomerulosclerosis - hypertensive nephropathy","bool":false}],"id":273},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2018"],"question":"Which one of these types of bladder diseases is correctly paired with the pathophysiology?","answers":[{"option":"Decreased vesicourethral angle - stress incontinence","bool":false},{"option":"Urethral injury - frequent voiding of urine","bool":false},{"option":"Prostatic hyperplasia - large volumes of urine","bool":false},{"option":"Tabes dorsalis - atonic bladder","bool":true},{"option":"Decreased detrusor activity - urge incontinence","bool":false}],"id":274},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs can be used to treat altitude sickness?","answers":[{"option":"Furosemide","bool":false},{"option":"Mannitol","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrochlorothiazide","bool":false},{"option":"Ethacrynic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Acetazolamide","bool":true}],"id":275},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"For individuals with latex allergy, which material of Foley's catheter is the next choice?","answers":[{"option":"Silicone","bool":true},{"option":"Plastic","bool":false},{"option":"Polyvinyl chloride (PVC)","bool":false},{"option":"Teflon","bool":false},{"option":"Silver","bool":false}],"id":276},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the percentage of filtered urea reabsorbed in kidneys per day?","answers":[{"option":"20%","bool":false},{"option":"1%","bool":false},{"option":"99.9%","bool":false},{"option":"30%","bool":false},{"option":"50%","bool":true}],"id":277},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"When do pronephroi degenerate during fetal development?","answers":[{"option":"At the end of 6th week","bool":false},{"option":"At the end of 3rd week","bool":false},{"option":"At the end of 4th week","bool":true},{"option":"At the end of 5th week","bool":false},{"option":"At the end of 2nd week","bool":false}],"id":278},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following structures is not present posterior to the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Quadratus femoris","bool":true},{"option":"Transversus abdominis","bool":false},{"option":"Ilioinguinal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Iliohypogastric nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Psoas major","bool":false}],"id":279},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"A 45-year-old patient is brought to the emergency room in a delirious state with weakness, blurred vision, dehydration, and hypothermia. On examination, he has a rapid pulse and his breathing is deep and labored, with a sickly sweet odor. His blood glucose is 256 mg/dL and his urinary dipstick shows +2 ketonuria. What is most likely the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Type 1 diabetes mellitus","bool":true},{"option":"Lactic acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Addison's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Acute renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Type 2 diabetes mellitus","bool":false}],"id":280},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following component of blood is the least filtered in the renal corpuscle?","answers":[{"option":"Lactic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":true},{"option":"Water","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Amino acid","bool":false}],"id":281},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the innermost covering of the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Fibrous capsule","bool":true},{"option":"Paranephric fat","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Renal fascia","bool":false},{"option":"Perinephric fat","bool":false}],"id":282},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is true about ureters?","answers":[{"option":"They arise from anterior side of kidney through vertical slits called hila","bool":false},{"option":"Ureters are retroperitoneal","bool":true},{"option":"Ureters are intraperitoneal","bool":false},{"option":"They are constricted at two regions","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":283},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the first step in pyrimidine synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Formation of carbamoyl phosphate","bool":true},{"option":"Formation of carbamoylaspartate","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Formation of orotate","bool":false},{"option":"Formation of phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate (PRPP)","bool":false}],"id":284},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not a source of nitrogen for de novo purine synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Aspartate","bool":false},{"option":"Glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamine","bool":false},{"option":"Alanine","bool":true},{"option":"All of these are a source of nitrogen for purine synthesis","bool":false}],"id":285},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is correct about the quality of pain in the case of nephrolithiasis?","answers":[{"option":"No pain is felt","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Pain is mild and is only felt when urinating","bool":false},{"option":"Pain is localized to kidneys","bool":false},{"option":"Pain radiates to back, flank, and groin region","bool":true}],"id":286},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is an inhibitor of xanthine oxidase?","answers":[{"option":"Mycophenolic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Allopurinol","bool":true},{"option":"5-fluorouracil","bool":false},{"option":"Methotrexate","bool":false},{"option":"Hydroxyurea","bool":false}],"id":287},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is correct about the urinary bladder?","answers":[{"option":"It has a layer of skeletal muscle that enables it to contract","bool":false},{"option":"It stores urine and has transitional epithelium","bool":true},{"option":"It consists of four muscular layers","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"It stores urine and has pseudostratified columnar epithelium","bool":false}],"id":288},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following are the functional units of the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Minor calices","bool":false},{"option":"Renal corpuscles","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrons","bool":true},{"option":"Medullary rays","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pyramids","bool":false}],"id":289},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Hydrogen ion reabsorption and secretion in proximal convoluted tubule is closely regulated with which of the following ions?","answers":[{"option":"K+","bool":false},{"option":"OH-","bool":false},{"option":"Mg+2","bool":false},{"option":"Cl-","bool":false},{"option":"Na+","bool":true}],"id":290},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"The kidney is connected to the bladder through which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Transversalis fascia","bool":false},{"option":"Lumber nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Perinephric fat","bool":false},{"option":"Ureters","bool":true},{"option":"Aorta","bool":false}],"id":291},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not one of the lines of the parallelogram of Morris used to identify the kidneys from the surface of the back?","answers":[{"option":"Vertical line 9.5 cm from the middle line","bool":false},{"option":"Horizontal border at the level of L1","bool":true},{"option":"Horizontal border at the level of the tips of the spinous process of T11","bool":false},{"option":"Vertical line 2.5 cm from the middle line","bool":false},{"option":"Horizontal border of the spinous process of L3","bool":false}],"id":292},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is seen in compensated metabolic alkalosis?","answers":[{"option":"HCO3- level is increased and pCO2 level is decreased","bool":false},{"option":"HCO3- level is decreased and pCO2 level is increased","bool":false},{"option":"HCO3- and pCO2 levels are decreased in blood","bool":false},{"option":"HCO3- and pCO2 levels are increased in blood","bool":true},{"option":"HCO3- level is increased and pCO2 level is in normal range","bool":false}],"id":293},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following products of the kidney helps in the absorption of calcium in the intestines?","answers":[{"option":"24,25-dihydroxycholecalciferol","bool":false},{"option":"All of these","bool":false},{"option":"Calcidiol","bool":false},{"option":"1,25-dihydroxycholecalciferol","bool":true},{"option":"Erythropoietin","bool":false}],"id":294},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"From which of the following organs, water loss from the body does not occur?","answers":[{"option":"Muscles","bool":true},{"option":"Nose","bool":false},{"option":"Skin","bool":false},{"option":"Lungs","bool":false},{"option":"Kidneys","bool":false}],"id":295},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following favors glomerular filtration?","answers":[{"option":"Peritubular capillary hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's capsule colloid osmotic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular capillary colloid osmotic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's capsule hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular capillary hydrostatic pressure","bool":true}],"id":296},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Decrease in the sodium and chloride levels causes macula densa to do which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Stimulate juxtaglomerular cells to produce renin","bool":true},{"option":"Cause systemic vasodilation","bool":false},{"option":"Release angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE)","bool":false},{"option":"Stimulate juxtaglomerular cells to produce erythropoietin","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibit juxtaglomerular cells to prevent the release of prostaglandins","bool":false}],"id":297},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is correct about the wall of the urinary bladder?","answers":[{"option":"It consists of an outer smooth muscle layer and an inner skeletal muscle layer lined by transitional epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"It consists of a skeletal muscle layer lined by transitional epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"It consists of a smooth muscle layer lined by transitional epithelium","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"It consists of a smooth muscle layer lined by pseudostratified columnar epithelium","bool":false}],"id":298},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What causes urine to flow through a patent urachus to the umbilicus?","answers":[{"option":"Urachal fistula","bool":true},{"option":"Urachal cyst","bool":false},{"option":"Renal agenesis","bool":false},{"option":"Ectopic kidney in pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Urachal sinus","bool":false}],"id":299},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the osmolality of most concentrated urine?","answers":[{"option":"400 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"600 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"200 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"300 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"1200 mOsm/L","bool":true}],"id":300},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following contribute towards making the urine concentrated?","answers":[{"option":"Antidiuretic hormone and hypoosmotic medullary interstitium","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone and renin","bool":false},{"option":"Antidiuretic hormone and hyperosmotic medullary interstitium","bool":true},{"option":"Aldosterone and cortical nephrons","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone and hyperosmotic medullary interstitium","bool":false}],"id":301},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the osmolality of filtrate in Bowman's capsule?","answers":[{"option":"100 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"1200 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"400 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"300 mOsm/L","bool":true},{"option":"200 mOsm/L","bool":false}],"id":302},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most powerful diuretic?","answers":[{"option":"Spironolactone","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Amiloride","bool":false},{"option":"Furosemide","bool":true},{"option":"Acetazolamide","bool":false}],"id":303},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following would stimulate the release of antidiuretic hormone?","answers":[{"option":"Decreased osmolality of blood","bool":false},{"option":"Atrial natriuretic peptide","bool":false},{"option":"Increased osmolality of blood","bool":true},{"option":"Increase in blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in blood volume","bool":false}],"id":304},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of chronic renal failure?","answers":[{"option":"Central diabetes insipidus and hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes mellitus and hypotension","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrogenic diabetes insipidus and hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes mellitus and hypertension","bool":true}],"id":305},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Lesch Nyhan syndrome is due to a defect in which of the following processes?","answers":[{"option":"Purine biosynthesis","bool":false},{"option":"Purine degradation","bool":false},{"option":"Purine salvage","bool":true},{"option":"Pyrimidine degradation","bool":false},{"option":"Pyrimidine synthesis","bool":false}],"id":306},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following urea transporters are affected by antidiuretic hormone?","answers":[{"option":"UT-A1 and UT-A3","bool":true},{"option":"UT-A2 and UT-A4","bool":false},{"option":"No urea transporter is affected by antidiuretic hormone","bool":false},{"option":"UT-A2 and UT-A3","bool":false},{"option":"UT-A1 and UT-A2","bool":false}],"id":307},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"A 12-year-old girl is brought to the clinic because of swelling around her eyes. On physical examination, she is afebrile and has periorbital edema. Laboratory findings show proteinuria on dipstick urinalysis, but no gross or microscopic hematuria. Microscopic examination of the urine shows numerous oval fat bodies. Serum creatinine level is 2.3 mg/dL. On electron microscopy, effacement of foot processes is seen. What is most likely the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Poststreptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Pyelonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Cystitis","bool":false},{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":true},{"option":"Acute kidney injury","bool":false}],"id":308},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What will be the effect on the size of kidneys of a person who is suffering from end-stage renal disease and has been on prolonged dialysis?","answers":[{"option":"Kidneys will increase in size","bool":false},{"option":"The size of kidneys will not be affected","bool":false},{"option":"Kidneys will reduce in size","bool":true},{"option":"The size of kidneys will first increase and then decrease","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":309},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Normal anion gap with metabolic acidosis is seen in which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic kidney disease","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Lactic acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Ketoacidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal tubular acidosis","bool":true}],"id":310},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis causes which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Urinary tract infection","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Alport syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrolithiasis","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrotic syndrome","bool":false}],"id":311},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is an example of loop diuretics?","answers":[{"option":"Bumetanide","bool":true},{"option":"Indapamide","bool":false},{"option":"Chlorthalidone","bool":false},{"option":"Metolazone","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrochlorothiazide","bool":false}],"id":312},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Mammals other than primates synthesize which of the following substances from uric acid?","answers":[{"option":"Glyoxylic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Ammonia","bool":false},{"option":"Urea","bool":false},{"option":"It is excreted directly in urine without being converted into any other substance","bool":false},{"option":"Allantoin","bool":true}],"id":313},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Megaloblastic anemia is associated with which of the following defects in nucleotide metabolism?","answers":[{"option":"Lesch-Nyhan syndrome (LNS)","bool":false},{"option":"Orotic aciduria","bool":true},{"option":"Hyperuricemia and gout","bool":false},{"option":"Adenosine deaminase deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":314},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following causes an increase in blood pressure?","answers":[{"option":"Atrial natriuretic peptide","bool":false},{"option":"Renin angiotensin and aldosterone system","bool":true},{"option":"Erythropoietin","bool":false},{"option":"Nitric oxide","bool":false},{"option":"Prostaglandin E","bool":false}],"id":315},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Ribosyl moiety in purine synthesis is donated by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Glutamine","bool":false},{"option":"Inosine monophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate","bool":true},{"option":"Tetrahydrofolate","bool":false},{"option":"Aspartate","bool":false}],"id":316},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the width of the filtration slit that separates the adjacent foot processes of podocytes?","answers":[{"option":"30 nm","bool":false},{"option":"9 nm","bool":false},{"option":"25 nm","bool":false},{"option":"40 nm","bool":true},{"option":"20 nm","bool":false}],"id":317},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a disease that includes the proliferation of cells, infiltration of leukocytes, and deposition of immune complexes in glomerular mesangium and basement membrane?","answers":[{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Poststreptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis (MPGN)","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":318},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is correct about pure water?","answers":[{"option":"It acts as a solvent and is a bad conductor of current","bool":true},{"option":"It acts as a solute and is a bad conductor of current","bool":false},{"option":"It acts as a solute","bool":false},{"option":"It is a good conductor of current","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":319},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most preferred fluid to be given to a hypovolemic patient?","answers":[{"option":"2/3% normal saline","bool":false},{"option":"0.9% normal saline","bool":true},{"option":"5% dextrose","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"1/3% normal saline","bool":false}],"id":320},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"A person has lost a lot of blood in a traumatic accident. What should be given to him immediately?","answers":[{"option":"Haemaccel","bool":true},{"option":"2% normal saline","bool":false},{"option":"5% dextrose","bool":false},{"option":"3% normal saline","bool":false},{"option":"Ringer's lactate solution","bool":false}],"id":321},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Proteins are reabsorbed in the renal tubule by which of the following processes?","answers":[{"option":"Paracellular transport","bool":false},{"option":"Phagocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary active transport","bool":false},{"option":"Passive transport","bool":false},{"option":"Pinocytosis","bool":true}],"id":322},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"An increase in extracellular fluid osmolarity causes special nerve cells called osmoreceptor cells to stimulate the release of antidiuretic hormone (ADH) from the posterior pituitary gland. Where in the brain are these osmoreceptors located?","answers":[{"option":"Pineal gland","bool":false},{"option":"Thalamus","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothalamus","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebellum","bool":false},{"option":"Brainstem","bool":false}],"id":323},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following parts of the urinary tract is not a common site for stone formation?","answers":[{"option":"Urethra","bool":true},{"option":"Ureters","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Renal calyces","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false}],"id":324},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Kussmaul's breathing is characterized by a deep, rapid breathing pattern that is seen with diabetic ketoacidosis. What is the role of Kussmaul's breathing?","answers":[{"option":"To blow out excessive carbon dioxide to increase blood pH","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"To increase blood oxygen concentration","bool":false},{"option":"To decrease volatile ketones from blood by exhaling them out","bool":false},{"option":"To blow out excessive carbon dioxide to lower blood pH","bool":false}],"id":325},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the reason behind polyuria seen in diabetes?","answers":[{"option":"Increased hydrostatic pressure in Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased synthesis of antidiuretic hormone (ADH)","bool":false},{"option":"Excess levels of sugar in urine","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Improper tubular reabsorption of solutes","bool":false}],"id":326},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the combined blood flow through both kidneys in a normal adult man?","answers":[{"option":"1300 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"750 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"1100 ml/min","bool":true},{"option":"150 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"500 ml/min","bool":false}],"id":327},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following urine findings is observed in case of an infection with group A beta-hemolytic post-streptococcal infection?","answers":[{"option":"Massive proteinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Polyuria","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cell casts","bool":true},{"option":"Waxy casts","bool":false}],"id":328},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"The least dilated part of male urethra develops from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Allantois","bool":false},{"option":"Surface ectoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Vesical part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic part of urogenital sinus","bool":true},{"option":"Phallic part of urogenital sinus","bool":false}],"id":329},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Regarding glomerular diseases, which of the following has hump-like deposits appearing as electron microscope findings?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":true}],"id":330},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Ureter in female pelvis is present in close association with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Fallopian tube","bool":false},{"option":"Ovarian artery","bool":false},{"option":"Body of uterus","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior vesical artery","bool":false},{"option":"Uterine artery","bool":true}],"id":331},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following renal calculi are larger and have a radiolucent appearance on X-ray?","answers":[{"option":"Uric acid stones","bool":true},{"option":"Magnesium ammonium phosphate stones","bool":false},{"option":"Cystine stones","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium phosphate stones","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium oxalate stones","bool":false}],"id":332},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following can be a chronic complication of diabetes type 1?","answers":[{"option":"Hyperosmolar hyperosmotic syndrome (HHS)","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoglycemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperglycemia","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetic ketoacidosis (DKA)","bool":true},{"option":"Atherosclerosis","bool":false}],"id":333},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following supplies blood to the abdominal ureter?","answers":[{"option":"Renal artery","bool":true},{"option":"Abdominal aorta","bool":false},{"option":"Uterine vessels","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior vena cava","bool":false},{"option":"Arcuate artery","bool":false}],"id":334},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"The renal arterioles are the branch of which of the following arteries?","answers":[{"option":"Abdominal aorta","bool":false},{"option":"Interlobar artery","bool":false},{"option":"Arcuate artery","bool":false},{"option":"Interlobular artery","bool":true},{"option":"Renal artery","bool":false}],"id":335},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following radio-opaque dye is commonly used in intravenous pyelogram?","answers":[{"option":"Gadolinium","bool":false},{"option":"Urografin","bool":true},{"option":"Gastrografin","bool":false},{"option":"Tecnitium","bool":false},{"option":"Barium Sulphate","bool":false}],"id":336},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Antidiuretic hormone stimulates water reabsorption by stimulating which channel in the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Transient receptor potential channel","bool":false},{"option":"Polycystin 2","bool":false},{"option":"Renal potassium channel","bool":false},{"option":"Aquaporin 2","bool":true},{"option":"Na⁺/K⁺/2Cl⁻ co-transporter channel","bool":false}],"id":337},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Where are the podocytes found in the renal corpuscle?","answers":[{"option":"Parietal layer of epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Mesangium","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's space","bool":false},{"option":"Visceral layer of epithelium","bool":true},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false}],"id":338},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following changes will occur if there is an addition of isotonic solution to a kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Plasma to interstitial shift","bool":true},{"option":"Interstitial to plasma shift","bool":false},{"option":"No change","bool":false},{"option":"Interstitial to intracellular shift","bool":false},{"option":"Intracellular to interstitial shift","bool":false}],"id":339},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"An intravenous pyelogram identifies renal calculi present much above the bladder in a patient. What is the probable site of renal calculi?","answers":[{"option":"Ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Renal calyces","bool":true},{"option":"Renal cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Renal medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Papilla","bool":false}],"id":340},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"A 16-year-old female presents to the outpatient department with mild dehydration due to vomiting. Upon examination, her renal function is found normal. Which of the following should be given to stabilize the patient's condition?","answers":[{"option":"0.45% saline solution","bool":false},{"option":"5% dextrose solution","bool":true},{"option":"10% dextrose solution","bool":false},{"option":"Ringer's lactate solution","bool":false},{"option":"3% saline solution","bool":false}],"id":341},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"A 65-year-old male presents to the outpatient department with the complaint of fatigue, weakness, loss of appetite, and decreased mental sharpness. He has a history of diabetes. The results of his blood picture shows: hemoglobin: 8.4 gm/dL, creatinine: 5 mg/dL, calcium: 6.3 mg/dL, and phosphate: 5.2 U/L. What is the possible cause of his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Renal calculi","bool":false},{"option":"Polycystic kidney disease","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic renal disease","bool":true},{"option":"Tubular necrosis","bool":false}],"id":342},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Bicarbonate and other buffers keep the pH of extracellular fluid regulated in what range?","answers":[{"option":"9.35-9.45","bool":false},{"option":"6.35-6.45","bool":false},{"option":"7.45-7.46","bool":false},{"option":"8.35-8.45","bool":false},{"option":"7.34-7.45","bool":true}],"id":343},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"The findings of an intravenous pyelogram reveal a renal stone lodged in a patient's ureter above the bladder. What is the possible location of the stone?","answers":[{"option":"Uterosacral ligament","bool":false},{"option":"Intramural ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Abdominal ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic brim","bool":true},{"option":"Ureterovesical junction","bool":false}],"id":344},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"As the ureter passes the anterior surface of the psoas major muscle in the abdomen, which nerve does it cross?","answers":[{"option":"Intercostal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Genitofemoral nerve","bool":true},{"option":"Hypogastric nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Ilioinguinal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Splanchnic nerve","bool":false}],"id":345},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which hormone stimulates the increased absorption of sodium?","answers":[{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":true},{"option":"Angiotensin","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-diuretic hormone","bool":false},{"option":"Erythropoietin","bool":false},{"option":"Calcitriol","bool":false}],"id":346},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following renal stones are radiopaque in appearance, large in size and increase the total leukocyte count?","answers":[{"option":"Calcium oxalate stones","bool":false},{"option":"Struvite stones","bool":true},{"option":"Cystine stones","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium phosphate stones","bool":false},{"option":"Uric acid stones","bool":false}],"id":347},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the value of one-third of the body fluid?","answers":[{"option":"14 L","bool":true},{"option":"10 L","bool":false},{"option":"12 L","bool":false},{"option":"15 L","bool":false},{"option":"13 L","bool":false}],"id":348},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following symptoms differentiate acute pyelonephritis from urinary tract infection?","answers":[{"option":"White blood cells cast","bool":true},{"option":"Proteinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Hematuria","bool":false},{"option":"Joint tenderness","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false}],"id":349},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following conditions cannot be stabilized by infusion of Haemaccel?","answers":[{"option":"Simple dehydration","bool":true},{"option":"Blood loss","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma loss","bool":false},{"option":"Severe dehydration","bool":false},{"option":"Volume deficiency shock","bool":false}],"id":350},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following drugs commonly causes renal problems?","answers":[{"option":"Cephalosporins","bool":false},{"option":"Paracetamol","bool":false},{"option":"Penicillins","bool":false},{"option":"Beta blockers","bool":false},{"option":"ACE inhibitors","bool":true}],"id":351},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is an example of secondary glomerulonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Systemic amyloidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Membranous nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Goodpasture syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Alport syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Berger disease","bool":false}],"id":352},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a characteristic feature of toxic acute tubular injury?","answers":[{"option":"Glomerulosclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Focal necrosis in proximal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Hyperactive state of mind","bool":false},{"option":"Neoplastic lesions in the kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased levels of blood urea nitrogen","bool":false}],"id":353},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following makes the urine more concentrated?","answers":[{"option":"Inhibition of aldosterone release","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced blood flow in medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease in the activity of Na/K pumps in basolateral membrane","bool":false},{"option":"Hyaline casts in urine","bool":false},{"option":"Release of anti-diuretic hormone","bool":true}],"id":354},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following parts of the nephron dilutes the urine?","answers":[{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Descending limb of loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Ascending limb of loop of Henle","bool":true}],"id":355},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"The tip of the renal pyramid opens into which of the following structures?","answers":[{"option":"Renal papillae","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Minor calyx","bool":true}],"id":356},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following structures can be found in the renal sinus?","answers":[{"option":"Major calyx","bool":true},{"option":"Renal cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false},{"option":"Medulla","bool":false}],"id":357},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"The blood vessels enter the kidney at which of the following structures?","answers":[{"option":"Hilum","bool":true},{"option":"Major calyx","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal column","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pyramid","bool":false}],"id":358},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following defines the bed capacity in a hospital?","answers":[{"option":"Total number of beds during a specific period","bool":false},{"option":"Average number of beds occupied by patients during a specific period","bool":false},{"option":"Total number of beds occupied by patients during a specific period","bool":false},{"option":"Average number of beds during a specific period","bool":true},{"option":"Average number of unoccupied beds during a specific period","bool":false}],"id":359},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"A 52-year-old female presents to the outpatient department with a history of diabetes for the past 20 years. Her blood picture shows HbA1C: 8.5%, and her urinalysis shows smoky urine. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Poor glycemic control","bool":false},{"option":"Nephropathy","bool":true},{"option":"Urinary tract infection","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulosclerosis","bool":false}],"id":360},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What is the mechanism behind glomerular basement membrane thickening?","answers":[{"option":"Deposition of calcium","bool":false},{"option":"Uric acid build-up on the membrane","bool":false},{"option":"Necrotic patch formation","bool":false},{"option":"All of them","bool":false},{"option":"Advanced glycosylated end products","bool":true}],"id":361},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"At which stage of the disease is glomerular capillary pressure high?","answers":[{"option":"Recovery stage of disease","bool":false},{"option":"Acute stage of disease","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic stage of disease","bool":false},{"option":"Convalescence stage of disease","bool":false},{"option":"Early stages of disease","bool":true}],"id":362},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following obstruction of structure causes bilateral hydronephrosis and an enlarged bladder?","answers":[{"option":"Ureterovesical junction obstruction","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder neck and urethral obstruction","bool":true},{"option":"Bladder fundus obstruction","bool":false},{"option":"Ureteropelvic junction obstruction","bool":false},{"option":"Renal obstruction","bool":false}],"id":363},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Upon examination of a patient, he is found to have a flat face and edema. His urinalysis reveals hematuria and oliguria. What is the person most likely suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Ureteral obstruction","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Nephrotic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Renal stones","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary tract infection","bool":false}],"id":364},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Reactions being catalyzed by hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyltransferase (HGPRT) require how much energy?","answers":[{"option":"0 ATP","bool":true},{"option":"1 ATP","bool":false},{"option":"4 ATPs","bool":false},{"option":"2 ATPs","bool":false},{"option":"3 ATPs","bool":false}],"id":365},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is incorrect regarding the sodium reabsorption in the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"It is transported by sodium hydrogen ATPases","bool":false},{"option":"There is a 80% sodium tubular load","bool":true},{"option":"65% of sodium reabsorption takes place in it","bool":false},{"option":"It shares a common carrier with glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Gradient is maintained by Na⁺/K⁺ pump","bool":false}],"id":366},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following hormones would increase with the subsequent increase in plasma's potassium concentration?","answers":[{"option":"Angiotensin-II","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-diuretic hormone","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":true},{"option":"Atrial natriuretic peptide","bool":false},{"option":"Renin","bool":false}],"id":367},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a ribonucleotide reductase coenzyme?","answers":[{"option":"Riboflavin","bool":false},{"option":"Thioredoxin","bool":true},{"option":"Thiamine","bool":false},{"option":"Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide + hydrogen (NADH)","bool":false},{"option":"Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide phosphate + hydrogen (NADPH)","bool":false}],"id":368},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Graft response does not depend upon which of the following factors?","answers":[{"option":"Previous skin infection","bool":true},{"option":"Gender","bool":false},{"option":"Etiology of renal disease","bool":false},{"option":"Cause of death of donor","bool":false},{"option":"Race","bool":false}],"id":369},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a reason for alkaline pH of urine?","answers":[{"option":"Reduced hydrogen ion secretion by tubules leading to more potassium ion retention","bool":false},{"option":"None of them","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced hydrogen ion secretion by tubules leading to more bicarbonate retention","bool":true},{"option":"Increased hydrogen ion secretion by tubules leading to more bicarbonate secretion","bool":false},{"option":"Increased hydrogen ion secretion by tubules leading to more potassium ion secretion","bool":false}],"id":370},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"What does a positive test for leukocyte esterase indicate?","answers":[{"option":"Presence of red blood cells","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of inflammatory cells","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of T-lymphocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of white blood cells","bool":true}],"id":371},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"A positive nitrite test shows the possibility of infection by which organism?","answers":[{"option":"Gram positive bacteria","bool":false},{"option":"Gram negative bacteria","bool":true},{"option":"Fungus","bool":false},{"option":"Virus","bool":false},{"option":"Protozoa","bool":false}],"id":372},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"Which cells appear in the urine when the specific gravity of urine is less than normal?","answers":[{"option":"Intercalated cells","bool":false},{"option":"Tubular epithelial cells","bool":true},{"option":"Juxtaglomerular cells","bool":false},{"option":"Interstitial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Podocytes","bool":false}],"id":373},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2019"],"question":"A 45-year-old woman comes to the outpatient department with complaints of weight loss and poor appetite. She has edema, shortness of breath, tiredness,  hematuria, urinary frequency, insomnia, and itchy skin. What is the most likely diagnosis for her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Sarcoidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Primary hyperparathyroidism","bool":false},{"option":"Osteomalacia","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic renal disease","bool":true},{"option":"Multiple myeloma","bool":false}],"id":374},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"The nephron is the functional unit of the kidney responsible for the filtration of plasma. It consists of which two major components?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule and distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Renal corpuscle and loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Renal tubule and collecting tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Renal corpuscle and renal tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule and loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":375},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 10-year-old girl complained of increasing fatigue and passing dark-colored urine for one week. She had a sore throat two weeks ago. On physical examination, there is no fever, and blood pressure is 140/90 mmHg. Laboratory studies show her serum creatinine is 2.8 mg/dL and urea nitrogen 24 mg/dL. Urinalysis shows 2+ blood, 1+ protein, no glucose, and no ketones. Microscopic urinalysis shows dysmorphic RBCs. A renal biopsy on microscopic examination shows glomerular hypercellularity, with polymorphonuclear leukocytes (PMNs) present. Electron microscopy shows subepithelial electron-dense humps. Which of the following laboratory findings is most likely to be present in this girl?","answers":[{"option":"Antibody to double stranded DNA","bool":false},{"option":"Elevated antistreptolysin O (ASO) titer","bool":true},{"option":"Anti-glomerular basement membrane antibody","bool":false},{"option":"Elevated serum glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Positive C3 nephritogenic factor","bool":false}],"id":376},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 38-year-old woman came with severe suprapubic pain. Urine analysis showed neutrophils without a cast, cloudy, and foul-smelling urine. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hydronephrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute cystitis","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic cystitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute pyelonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic pyelonephritis","bool":false}],"id":377},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 10-year-boy is admitted to the ward with the complaint of urinary retention. A Foley catheter is passed to relieve the retention. How much length of catheter should be inserted before inflating the balloon of catheter?","answers":[{"option":"3-5 cm of catheter length","bool":false},{"option":"When the urine starts flowing","bool":false},{"option":"Half the length of catheter","bool":false},{"option":"Just tip of the catheter","bool":false},{"option":"Entire length of the catheter","bool":true}],"id":378},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A second-year medical student is looking at the histology slide of tissue with small-caliber lined by transitional epithelium and also observes three layers of smooth muscles in its wall.  He is looking at a slide of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Vas deferens","bool":false},{"option":"Urethra","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter","bool":true},{"option":"Prostate","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary bladder","bool":false}],"id":379},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 30-year-old pregnant lady is going for an emergency cesarean section. She is being catheterized before the procedure. Which one is the most recurrent complication of urinary catheterization?","answers":[{"option":"Pyelonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary tract infection","bool":true},{"option":"Nephrolithiasis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal inflammation","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue trauma","bool":false}],"id":380},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 35-year-old male presents with features of nephrotic syndrome. In addition, there is microscopic haematuria. Renal biopsy shows partial sclerosis affecting some of the glomeruli. Sclerosed areas show IgM and C3 on immunofluorescence. What is the most likely diagnosis in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Membranous nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Acute post infectious glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":false},{"option":"Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis","bool":true},{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false}],"id":381},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 4-year-old girl is brought to the hospital with complaints of continuous dribbling of urine. On examination, the urine was coming out of the vagina. The possible cause of this embryological anomaly may be due to which of these?","answers":[{"option":"Formation of vaginal fistula","bool":true},{"option":"Ureter opening into the base of urinary bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter opening into the urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter opening into cloaca","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter opening into paramesonephric duct","bool":false}],"id":382},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following clinical symptoms differentiates pyelonephritis from cystitis?","answers":[{"option":"Dysuria","bool":false},{"option":"Hematuria","bool":false},{"option":"Fever","bool":true},{"option":"Polyuria","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia","bool":false}],"id":383},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is a method to excrete excess water?","answers":[{"option":"Increased respiratory rate","bool":false},{"option":"Diarrhea","bool":false},{"option":"Polyuria","bool":true},{"option":"Oliguria","bool":false},{"option":"Sweating","bool":false}],"id":384},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 40-year-old businesswoman came to the outpatient department for the workup of her recurrent renal stone disease. She has already undergone multiple investigations and now she is insisting to go for magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). How will you counsel her that for her particular disease, MRI is not a suitable modality?","answers":[{"option":"MRI works under the principle of magnetism","bool":false},{"option":"No ionization radiation burden is present in MRI","bool":false},{"option":"MRI is an expensive modality","bool":false},{"option":"MRI reporting is difficult","bool":false},{"option":"Calcification/calcific densities are detected with difficulty by MRI","bool":true}],"id":385},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 43-year-old man complains of malaise for 3 weeks. On examination, his blood pressure is 150/95 mm Hg, and presents with pitting edema of the lower extremities. Urinalysis shows no glucose, blood, ketones, nitrite, or urobilinogen, and the microscopic urinalysis reveals no RBC/HPF and only 1 WBC/HPF, 24-hour urine protein is 4.1 gm, serum creatinine is 3.5 mg/dL with urea nitrogen of 38 mg/dL. His hepatitis B surface antigen is positive. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Membranous nephropathy","bool":true},{"option":"Diabetic nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Post streptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":false}],"id":386},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy has had swelling around his eyes for one week, and he has been lethargic. On examination, he has periorbital edema. His temperature is 37°C, pulse is 75 bpm, respiratory rate is 22/minute, and blood pressure is 140/90 mmHg. Urine examination shows a specific gravity of 1.010 and a pH of 6.5, with 4+ protein, no glucose, no blood, no casts, and no ketones. Microscopic urinalysis exhibits fat bodies, but no leukocytes or erythrocytes. He improves with corticosteroid therapy. Which of the following is the most likely lesion in the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Hyperplastic arteriosclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular crescent formation","bool":false},{"option":"Immune complex deposition in the mesangium","bool":false},{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Effacement of podocyte foot processes","bool":true}],"id":387},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 6-year-old boy presents with generalized edema and periorbital edema. Further investigations show hypoalbuminemia, lipiduria, and 3.6 g proteinuria. Renal biopsy and electron microscopy are carried out. Which of the following electron microscopic features do you expect to find in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Subepithelial humps","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of foot processes, no deposits","bool":true},{"option":"Dense mesangial deposits","bool":false},{"option":"Subendothelial deposits","bool":false},{"option":"Linear deposits of IgG in the glomerular basement membrane","bool":false}],"id":388},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A child after a streptococcal infection presents 10 days later with hypertension, hematuria, edema, and sometimes oliguria. There appear to be elevated titers of anti-streptolysin O antibodies. What is the key morphological feature of his disease?","answers":[{"option":"Humps and deposition of IgG and C3","bool":true},{"option":"Humps","bool":false},{"option":"Deposition of IgG and C3","bool":false},{"option":"Deposition of IgM and C3","bool":false},{"option":"Spike and dome appearance","bool":false}],"id":389},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A filterability of 1.0 means that the substance is filtered as freely as water, whereas a filterability of 0.75 means that the substance is filtered only 75%. Which of the following substance has a filterability of only 75 percent as rapidly as water?","answers":[{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Myoglobin","bool":true},{"option":"Inulin","bool":false}],"id":390},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A normal 70 kg human must excrete about how many milliosmoles of solute each day?","answers":[{"option":"400","bool":false},{"option":"200","bool":false},{"option":"1000","bool":false},{"option":"600","bool":true},{"option":"800","bool":false}],"id":391},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the research study design in which diseased people are selected and then compared with the non-diseased people to find out the risk factors of the disease called?","answers":[{"option":"Cross-sectional study","bool":false},{"option":"Case report study","bool":false},{"option":"Case control study","bool":true},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":false},{"option":"Case series study","bool":false}],"id":392},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is a water molecule with an electrical charge distributed asymmetrically about its structure referred to as?","answers":[{"option":"Pentapolar","bool":false},{"option":"Unipolar","bool":false},{"option":"Tripolar","bool":false},{"option":"Dipolar","bool":true},{"option":"Tetrapolar","bool":false}],"id":393},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A young male presented in a dehydrated state of moderate degree. His renal function is normal but he is unable to take fluid orally because of drowsiness and vomiting. Which of the following intravenous fluids is preferable to start first?","answers":[{"option":"3% saline","bool":false},{"option":"Distilled water","bool":false},{"option":"1/3 saline","bool":false},{"option":"Ringer's lactate","bool":false},{"option":"5% dextrose","bool":true}],"id":394},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"About 35% of the filtered load of sodium chloride is reabsorbed from which part of the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Thin limb - loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Cortical collecting tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Thick ascending limb of loop of Henle","bool":true},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":395},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"In chronic renal failure, anemia develops due to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Erythropoetin deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Blood loss","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow toxins","bool":false},{"option":"Red cell destruction","bool":false},{"option":"Bone marrow fibrosis","bool":false}],"id":396},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Considering the normal urine composition, what is the water content of it in percentage?","answers":[{"option":"75%","bool":false},{"option":"95%","bool":true},{"option":"85%","bool":false},{"option":"80%","bool":false},{"option":"90%","bool":false}],"id":397},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A decrease in sodium chloride levels causes the macula densa to do which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Dilatation of efferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Contraction of juxtaglomerular cells","bool":false},{"option":"Dilatation of afferent arterioles","bool":true},{"option":"Contraction of mesangial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of renin","bool":false}],"id":398},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"During a tutorial class on the microscopic structure of the kidney, specific features of each part of the nephron were being discussed. Which of the following is mismatched?","answers":[{"option":"Visceral layer of Bowman's capsule - podocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Thin segment of Henle's loop - simple squamous epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal tubule cells - many mitochondria; an ion-pumping cell","bool":false},{"option":"Parietal layer of Bowman's capsule - simple squamous epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Distal tubule cells - brush border","bool":true}],"id":399},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is true about the epithelium of navicular fossa of glans penis?","answers":[{"option":"Pseudostratified epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Simple squamous epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Columnar epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Stratified squamous keratinizing epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"Stratified squamous non-keratinizing epithelium","bool":true}],"id":400},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following factor causes an increase in the secretion of antidiuretic hormone (ADH)?","answers":[{"option":"Decrease in plasma osmolarity","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Hyponatremia","bool":false},{"option":"Intake of alcohol","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease in blood volume","bool":true}],"id":401},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding acute kidney injury (AKI)?","answers":[{"option":"Often reversible","bool":true},{"option":"Calcium levels are high","bool":false},{"option":"Always needs dialysis","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound shows small kidneys","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia is a predominant feature","bool":false}],"id":402},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is true for the overhydration state?","answers":[{"option":"Osmotic pressure increases in extracellular fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothalamus signals posterior pituitary to increase ADH (antidiuretic hormone) output","bool":false},{"option":"Osmoreceptors in hypothalamus are stimulated","bool":false},{"option":"Urine output decreases","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothalamus signals posterior pituitary to decrease ADH (antidiuretic hormone) output","bool":true}],"id":403},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"In pyelonephritis, what is the diagnostic urinary finding?","answers":[{"option":"Pus cell cast","bool":true},{"option":"Pus cells","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cell cast","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Red blood cells","bool":false}],"id":404},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"In response to acidosis, the kidneys may enhance which of these?","answers":[{"option":"Secretion of HCO3- ions","bool":false},{"option":"Nitrogen retention","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of H+ ions","bool":true},{"option":"Secretion of Na+ ions","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of K+ ions","bool":false}],"id":405},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"In response to alkalosis, the kidneys may enhance which of these?","answers":[{"option":"Nitrogen retention","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of HCO3- ions","bool":true},{"option":"Secretion of H+ ions","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of Na+ ions","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of K+ ions","bool":false}],"id":406},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"In a detailed urine report, dipstick mechanism checks for which of these?","answers":[{"option":"Infecting organism","bool":false},{"option":"Protein and glucose","bool":true},{"option":"Casts","bool":false},{"option":"Crystals","bool":false},{"option":"Cells","bool":false}],"id":407},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Renal retention of which of these ions is directly linked to an increase in extracellular fluid volume?","answers":[{"option":"K+ ions","bool":false},{"option":"Cl- ions","bool":false},{"option":"Na+ ions","bool":true},{"option":"HCO3- ions","bool":false},{"option":"H+ ions","bool":false}],"id":408},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What percentage of total body water is contained in the intracellular fluid?","answers":[{"option":"60%","bool":false},{"option":"30%","bool":false},{"option":"40%","bool":false},{"option":"50%","bool":false},{"option":"70%","bool":true}],"id":409},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Juxtaglomerular apparatus is a specialized structure located at the vascular pole of the glomerulus. Which of the following is true concerning the juxtaglomerular apparatus?","answers":[{"option":"The macula densa is part of the proximal tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Lacis cells are the specialized smooth muscle cells","bool":true},{"option":"The juxtaglomerular (JG) cells are modified epithelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"The juxtaglomerular (JG) cells are found equally in both the afferent and efferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Macula densa cells secrete renin","bool":false}],"id":410},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Juxtaglomerular apparatus is very important in blood pressure regulation. Which of the following structure is not its part?","answers":[{"option":"Podocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Juxtaglomerular cells (JG) cells","bool":false},{"option":"Macula densa","bool":false},{"option":"Polkissen cells","bool":false},{"option":"Extra glomerular mesangial cells","bool":false}],"id":411},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Lymphatics of kidneys drain into which nodes?","answers":[{"option":"Testicular nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Cystic nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Pre aortic nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral aortic nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Superficial inguinal nodes","bool":false}],"id":412},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following does the least dilated part of male urethra develops from?","answers":[{"option":"Fusion of urethral folds","bool":false},{"option":"Phallic part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Allantois","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic part of urogenital sinus","bool":true},{"option":"Wolffian duct","bool":false}],"id":413},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following steps comes after data collection?","answers":[{"option":"Formulate question","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothesis","bool":false},{"option":"Literature search","bool":false},{"option":"Development of research design","bool":false},{"option":"Data analysis","bool":true}],"id":414},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which one of the following is the first step of research?","answers":[{"option":"Literature search","bool":false},{"option":"Formulate questions","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothesis","bool":true},{"option":"Data collection","bool":false},{"option":"Develop research design","bool":false}],"id":415},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"How are membranous glomerulopathy and post-streptococcal glomerulonephritis similar?","answers":[{"option":"Both are self-limiting and transient renal diseases","bool":false},{"option":"Most commonly seen in children","bool":false},{"option":"Commonly associated with the nephrotic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Occur most frequently following an infectious disease","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular immune complex deposits","bool":true}],"id":416},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Mrs. X, a 30-year-old, recently married female, presented with a breast lump for the first time in the clinic. The doctor listened to her attentively but was insensitive towards her symptoms and complications. The doctor did not say or discuss anything but advised her to get the list of investigations done. She returned from the clinic more apprehensive and confused. What do you think, could most likely address her apprehensions?","answers":[{"option":"An attribute of cultural sensitivity","bool":false},{"option":"An attribute of empathy","bool":false},{"option":"By arranging an information care session","bool":true},{"option":"By offering emotional support","bool":false},{"option":"By addressing her misconceptions","bool":false}],"id":417},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"On discussing histological features of the kidney, the students were asked about the location of macula densa. What is its location?","answers":[{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":418},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Periureteric fascia is an extension of which of these?","answers":[{"option":"Paranephric fat","bool":false},{"option":"Renal fascia","bool":true},{"option":"Perinephric fat","bool":false},{"option":"Pararenal fat","bool":false},{"option":"Perirenal fat","bool":false}],"id":419},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What causes the reabsorption of bicarbonates from renal tubules?","answers":[{"option":"Retention of acid metabolites","bool":false},{"option":"Low acid secretion","bool":false},{"option":"Raised PCO2","bool":true},{"option":"Decreased NH3 formation","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased PCO2","bool":false}],"id":420},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is not true regarding blood supply to the kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"Inter lobular arteries are end arteries","bool":false},{"option":"Afferent glomerular arterioles arise mostly form arcuate arteries","bool":true},{"option":"Renal circulation is of portal type","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney is divided into five vascular segments","bool":false},{"option":"Medulla receives blood mostly from efferent arterioles of glomeruli","bool":false}],"id":421},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the approximate length of kidney?","answers":[{"option":"12 cm","bool":false},{"option":"10 cm","bool":true},{"option":"6-12 cm","bool":false},{"option":"8-9 cm","bool":false},{"option":"11-13 cm","bool":false}],"id":422},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Regarding glomerular diseases, which of the following is most likely the pathogenesis of glomerulonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Complement proteins do not play an important role in the pathogenesis","bool":false},{"option":"TGF-β released during nephritis leads to glomerular basement membrane thickening","bool":true},{"option":"In immune complex mediated nephritis, the autoantigen is characteristically glomerular","bool":false},{"option":"A causal role of T-cells in the pathogenesis has been strongly established by researchers","bool":false},{"option":"The pattern of antibody deposition in anti - GBM disease is radial in pattern","bool":false}],"id":423},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is ineffective in Addison's disease?","answers":[{"option":"Amiloride","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrocortisone","bool":false},{"option":"Triamterene","bool":false},{"option":"Spironolactone","bool":true},{"option":"Bumetanide","bool":false}],"id":424},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What are the regions of cortical parenchyma located between medullary pyramids rather than adjacent to the surface of the kidney called?","answers":[{"option":"Columns of Bertin","bool":true},{"option":"Papillae","bool":false},{"option":"Calyces","bool":false},{"option":"Medullary rays","bool":false},{"option":"Renal lobules","bool":false}],"id":425},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is responsible for glucose reabsorption in the S1 segment of the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"GLUT2 (glucose transporter-2)","bool":false},{"option":"GLUT3 (glucose transporter-3)","bool":false},{"option":"GLUT1 (glucose transporter-1)","bool":false},{"option":"SGLT1 (sodium-glucose cotransporter-1)","bool":false},{"option":"SGLT2 (sodium-glucose cotransporter-2)","bool":true}],"id":426},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Sodium retention through aldosterone-mediated renal regulation results in the elimination of which one of the following?","answers":[{"option":"HCO3- ions","bool":false},{"option":"NH3+ ions","bool":false},{"option":"Cl- ions","bool":false},{"option":"K+ ions","bool":true},{"option":"H+ ions","bool":false}],"id":427},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Where do the stretch signals for bladder emptying mainly originate?","answers":[{"option":"Ureter","bool":false},{"option":"Fundus of urinary bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Body of the bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior urethra","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior urethra","bool":true}],"id":428},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which type of transport facilitates the sodium absorption in distal convoluted tubule by Na pump across the basolateral membrane?","answers":[{"option":"Passive transport","bool":false},{"option":"Diffusion","bool":false},{"option":"Primary active transport","bool":true},{"option":"Facilitated diffusion","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary active transport","bool":false}],"id":429},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which structure is not related to the anterior surface of the right kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Right colic flexure","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":true},{"option":"Descending part of duodenum","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Suprarenal gland","bool":false}],"id":430},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"The distal part of the male urethra in the glans of the penis is derived from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Endoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral plate mesoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Intermediate mesoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Ectoderm","bool":true},{"option":"Paraxial mesoderm","bool":false}],"id":431},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following can the nephron be best defined as?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose transporter","bool":false},{"option":"A structural and functional unit of kidney","bool":true},{"option":"Storage site of lipids","bool":false},{"option":"Site of ADH (antidiuretic hormone) production","bool":false},{"option":"Cholesterol synthesizing body","bool":false}],"id":432},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following chemical substances inhibits the secretion of gastric acid?","answers":[{"option":"Gastrin","bool":false},{"option":"Secretin","bool":true},{"option":"Histamine","bool":false},{"option":"Gastric inhibitory peptide","bool":false},{"option":"Acetylcholine","bool":false}],"id":433},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"The greatest amount of hydrogen ion secreted by the proximal tubule is associated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Excretion of hydrogen ion","bool":false},{"option":"Reabsorption of calcium ion","bool":false},{"option":"Excretion of potassium ion","bool":false},{"option":"Reabsorption of phosphate ion","bool":false},{"option":"Reabsorption of bicarbonate ion","bool":true}],"id":434},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"In which of the following are Na-K-Cl cotransporters present in?","answers":[{"option":"Thick ascending limb of the loop of Henle","bool":true},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Thin ascending limb of the loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":435},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the large space, lined by transitional epithelium, which funnels urine into the ureter called?","answers":[{"option":"Pelvis","bool":true},{"option":"Capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Hilum","bool":false},{"option":"Papillae","bool":false},{"option":"Calyx","bool":false}],"id":436},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is the only part present in the medullary region?","answers":[{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":true},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false}],"id":437},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the normal glomerular capillary colloid osmotic pressure?","answers":[{"option":"18 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"32 mmHg","bool":true},{"option":"70 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"10 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"60 mmHg","bool":false}],"id":438},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the normal PO2 level in arterial blood?","answers":[{"option":"22-26 mm of Hg","bool":false},{"option":"<50 mm of Hg","bool":false},{"option":">100 mm of Hg","bool":false},{"option":"85-90 mm of Hg","bool":true},{"option":"35-45 mm of Hg","bool":false}],"id":439},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"The osmolality of the proximal convoluted tubule is the same as that of plasma, due to the presence of water channels on the basolateral membrane that causes reabsorption of water. Which water channels are present in the basolateral membrane of proximal convoluted tubules?","answers":[{"option":"Aquaporin-5","bool":false},{"option":"Aquaporin-3","bool":false},{"option":"Aquaporin-1","bool":true},{"option":"Aquaporin-4","bool":false},{"option":"Aquaporin-2","bool":false}],"id":440},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which part of the nephron exhibits brush border on microscopy?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Pars recta","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false}],"id":441},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"The severe constriction of efferent arterioles affects glomerular filtration rate (GFR) by which one of the following changes?","answers":[{"option":"It has no effect on GFR","bool":false},{"option":"Decreases GFR by increasing colloid osmotic force","bool":true},{"option":"Increases renal blood flow by afferent arteriole vasodilatation","bool":false},{"option":"Increases GFR by increasing colloid osmotic force","bool":false},{"option":"Increases GFR by increasing renal flow","bool":false}],"id":442},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Under the influence of parathyroid hormone, the renal reabsorption of calcium mainly occurs in which part of the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Renal papilla","bool":false},{"option":"Ascending thick limb of loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting ducts","bool":false}],"id":443},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What are the vessels that connect glomerular capillaries with peritubular capillaries called?","answers":[{"option":"Afferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":false},{"option":"Peritubular capillaries","bool":false},{"option":"Arcuate arteries","bool":false},{"option":"Efferent arterioles","bool":true}],"id":444},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which reflex is initiated when the ureter is blocked by the stone resulting in intense pain?","answers":[{"option":"Vesico-ureteric reflex","bool":false},{"option":"Ureteric reflex","bool":false},{"option":"Reno-vesical reflex","bool":false},{"option":"Vesical reflex","bool":false},{"option":"Uretero-renal reflex","bool":true}],"id":445},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following study design is also called a snap shot study?","answers":[{"option":"Case control study","bool":false},{"option":"Case series","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":false},{"option":"Case report study","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional study","bool":true}],"id":446},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Xanthine oxidase is catalytically important for the formation of uric acid along with which of these?","answers":[{"option":"H2O","bool":false},{"option":"HCO3-","bool":false},{"option":"H2O2","bool":false},{"option":"CO2","bool":false},{"option":"O2","bool":true}],"id":447},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"What is the major hormone involved in regulation of sodium and water balance in the body?","answers":[{"option":"Vasopressin","bool":false},{"option":"Epinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":true},{"option":"Antidiuretic hormone","bool":false},{"option":"Norepinephrine","bool":false}],"id":448},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following can be seen in the renal sinus?","answers":[{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false},{"option":"Renal cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pelvis","bool":true},{"option":"Medulla","bool":false}],"id":449},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is measured through the arterial blood gas (ABG) test?","answers":[{"option":"Anion gap","bool":false},{"option":"pH, pCO2 and pO2","bool":true},{"option":"Oxygen saturation","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine level","bool":false},{"option":"pCO2 and pO2","bool":false}],"id":450},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following correctly describes 'informational care'?","answers":[{"option":"Provision of information to patients about disease","bool":false},{"option":"Provision of information to patients about drugs and their side effects","bool":false},{"option":"Provision of information to patients about doctors","bool":false},{"option":"Provision of information to patients about disease, drugs, and doctors","bool":true},{"option":"Provision of information to patients about drugs and doctors","bool":false}],"id":451},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is most true for transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"Polycystic kidneys should be excluded from the list of allografts","bool":true},{"option":"HIV is the most contraindicated","bool":false},{"option":"Quality of life is increased after transplantation","bool":false},{"option":"Renal transplantation is reasonable for all end-stage renal diseases","bool":false},{"option":"Graft reaction occurs in poor patients","bool":false}],"id":452},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A patient came to the outpatient department with frequent urinary discharge. A complete urinalysis on agar medium was done and bacteria were found to be non-lactose fermenter, gram -ve, rod-shaped with no signs of swarming movement. Which of the following could be the cause?","answers":[{"option":"Proteus mirabilis","bool":false},{"option":"Enterococcus","bool":false},{"option":"E.coli","bool":false},{"option":"Pseudomonas","bool":true},{"option":"Proteus vulgaris","bool":false}],"id":453},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is effective in decreasing K+ ion secretion in the distal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"Potassium-sparing diuretic","bool":true},{"option":"Metronidazole","bool":false},{"option":"Thiazide diuretics","bool":false},{"option":"Acetaminophen","bool":false},{"option":"Loop diuretics","bool":false}],"id":454},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is not found anterior to the left kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Head of pancreas","bool":true},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Suprarenal gland","bool":false},{"option":"Looped jejenum","bool":false},{"option":"Splenic flexure","bool":false}],"id":455},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"Which of the following parts of the bladder expands when it is filled up completely?","answers":[{"option":"Trigone","bool":true},{"option":"Neck","bool":false},{"option":"Base","bool":false},{"option":"Fundus","bool":false},{"option":"Body","bool":false}],"id":456},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A 20-year-old man is brought into the emergency as he has overdosed on morphine. On examination, he is unconscious, pupils are pinpoint and nonreactive. Several injection marks are also seen on his arms. What is the immediate treatment to be precise after seeing breathing, and circulation?","answers":[{"option":"Naloxone","bool":true},{"option":"Naloxone + gastric lavage","bool":false},{"option":"Gastric lavage","bool":false},{"option":"Gastric lavage with tannic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Naloxone + pethidine","bool":false}],"id":457},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2020"],"question":"A couple married for four years was unable to conceive a pregnancy. A detailed analysis of the sperms of the husband revealed azoospermia. They were suggested to go for artificial insemination by a fertility specialist. Which type of procedure would best suit the couple?","answers":[{"option":"Artificial insemination donor","bool":true},{"option":"Artificial insemination homologous","bool":false},{"option":"Surrogacy","bool":false},{"option":"In vitro fertilization","bool":false},{"option":"Artificial insemination","bool":false}],"id":458},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the arrangement of structures at the hilum of the kidney from anterior to posterior?","answers":[{"option":"Renal pelvis, vein, artery","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Vein, artery, renal pelvis","bool":true},{"option":"Artery, vein, renal pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pelvis, artery, vein","bool":false}],"id":459},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"The nephron is the functional unit of a kidney. Which of the following structures does urine pass through before entering the ureter?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Renal pelvis","bool":true},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":460},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 63-year-old female came to the outpatient department with complaints of fever, peristaltic pain, and hematuria. Her ultrasound reports revealed calculi in the conducting part of the urinary system. Where are the calculi most likely found?","answers":[{"option":"Minor calyx","bool":false},{"option":"Major calyx","bool":false},{"option":"Ureterovesical part of ureter","bool":true},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal columns","bool":false}],"id":461},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the false statement regarding the posterior relations of the right kidney?","answers":[{"option":"12th rib","bool":false},{"option":"Quadratus lumborum","bool":false},{"option":"Psoas major","bool":false},{"option":"Iliohypogastric nerve","bool":false},{"option":"11th rib","bool":true}],"id":462},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following structures lie in the center of the renal lobule?","answers":[{"option":"Interlobar artery","bool":false},{"option":"Cortical column","bool":false},{"option":"Medullary ray","bool":true},{"option":"Arcuate artery","bool":false},{"option":"Renal hilum","bool":false}],"id":463},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 2nd-year medical student is looking at a histology slide of tissue with a narrow lumen lined by transitional epithelium. He can observe 3 layers of smooth muscles in its wall. Which structure is he observing?","answers":[{"option":"Vas deferens","bool":false},{"option":"Urethra","bool":false},{"option":"Prostate","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Ureter","bool":true}],"id":464},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following histological features is not specific to the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"They have striated borders due to basal infoldings of plasma membrane","bool":false},{"option":"They are lined by simple cuboidal/low columnar epithelium","bool":false},{"option":"They have microvilli on their luminal surfaces forming a brush border","bool":false},{"option":"They are more eosinophilic due to numerous mitochondria","bool":false},{"option":"They do not have a typical brush border as compared to the distal convoluted tubule","bool":true}],"id":465},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A double ureter anomaly results from the failure of normal development of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Metanephros","bool":false},{"option":"Pronephros","bool":false},{"option":"Mesonephros (Wolffian) duct","bool":false},{"option":"Ureteric bud","bool":true},{"option":"Paramesonephric duct","bool":false}],"id":466},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the most abundant buffer in the proximal tubular fluid?","answers":[{"option":"Ammonia","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphate","bool":true},{"option":"Lactate","bool":false},{"option":"Protein","bool":false},{"option":"Bicarbonate","bool":false}],"id":467},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the principle mechanism of H+ ion secretion into the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"H-ATPase","bool":false},{"option":"Na-H symport","bool":false},{"option":"Na-H exchanger","bool":true},{"option":"H-Ca exchanger","bool":false},{"option":"H-HCO₃-ATPase","bool":false}],"id":468},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"At what volume of urine, is the micturition reflex initiated?","answers":[{"option":"250 ml - 300 ml","bool":false},{"option":"150 ml -200 ml","bool":false},{"option":"300 ml - 400 ml","bool":true},{"option":"450 ml - 500 ml","bool":false},{"option":"100 ml - 150 ml","bool":false}],"id":469},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the dietary effect of high protein intake and increased blood glucose on renal nephrons?","answers":[{"option":"Increase Bowman's capsule hydrostatic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Increase afferent arteriolar constriction","bool":false},{"option":"Increase efferent arteriolar constriction","bool":false},{"option":"Increase glomerular colloid oncotic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Increase sodium reabsorption in proximal convoluted tubules","bool":true}],"id":470},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"The clearance of which endogenously produced substance is used to assess normal renal function?","answers":[{"option":"Urea","bool":false},{"option":"Para-amino hippuric acid (PAH)","bool":false},{"option":"Potassium ions","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine","bool":true},{"option":"Inulin","bool":false}],"id":471},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What do the kidneys enhance in response to alkalosis?","answers":[{"option":"N₂-retention","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of H⁺ ions","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of K⁺ ions","bool":false},{"option":"Secretion of HCO₃⁻","bool":true},{"option":"Secretion of Na⁺ ions","bool":false}],"id":472},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following will decrease the amount of potassium excreted from the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Circulating level of aldosterone increases","bool":false},{"option":"The excretion of organic ions increase","bool":false},{"option":"Na+ reabsorption by the distal nephron decreases","bool":true},{"option":"Dietary intake of potassium increases","bool":false},{"option":"Distal tubular flow increases","bool":false}],"id":473},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"How can the body get rid of the huge acid load produced by metabolic reactions?","answers":[{"option":"Breathe faster and more deeply","bool":false},{"option":"Increase the concentration of protein ions in the plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Excrete hydrogen ions into the urine","bool":true},{"option":"Increase lipids in the blood","bool":false},{"option":"Increase the concentration of sodium ions","bool":false}],"id":474},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy develops severe diarrhea while traveling to South Asia. The laboratory investigation revealed the following: arterial blood pH = 7.25, partial pressure of carbon dioxide = 24 mmHg, bicarbonate = 10 mEq/L, normal anion gap. What is the correct diagnosis of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Hypercapnea","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis","bool":true}],"id":475},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which hormone regulates sodium and water content in the human body?","answers":[{"option":"Prolactin","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-diuretic hormone","bool":true},{"option":"Oxytocin","bool":false},{"option":"Cortisone","bool":false},{"option":"Epinephrine","bool":false}],"id":476},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the normal plasma sodium concentration?","answers":[{"option":"135 to 145 mEq/L","bool":true},{"option":"85 to 105 mEq/L","bool":false},{"option":"35 to 75 mEq/L","bool":false},{"option":"155 to 175 mEq/L","bool":false},{"option":"115 to 125 mEq/L","bool":false}],"id":477},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Where is the largest portion of water (28 liters) present?","answers":[{"option":"Intracellular compartment","bool":true},{"option":"Blood","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Extracellular compartment","bool":false},{"option":"Interstitial compartment","bool":false}],"id":478},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Ionization of water is the basis of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Solubility","bool":false},{"option":"pH scale","bool":true},{"option":"Viscosity","bool":false},{"option":"Diffusion","bool":false},{"option":"Adsorption","bool":false}],"id":479},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the predominant cation of plasma?","answers":[{"option":"Ca⁺²","bool":false},{"option":"Mg⁺²","bool":false},{"option":"Fe⁺²","bool":false},{"option":"Na⁺","bool":true},{"option":"K⁺","bool":false}],"id":480},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the normal plasma potassium reference value?","answers":[{"option":"3.5 - 5.4 mEq/L","bool":true},{"option":"1 - 2.2 mEq/L","bool":false},{"option":"5.5 - 7.6 mEq/L","bool":false},{"option":"1.5 - 2.5 mEq/L","bool":false},{"option":"6.5 - 7.7 mEq/L","bool":false}],"id":481},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 41-year-old has had recurrent urinary tract infections for 15 years. On many of these occasions, Proteus mirabilis was cultured from his urine. For the past 4 days, he has had burning pain while urinating, and urinary frequency. On examination, his temperature is 37.9°C, pulse is 70/min, and blood pressure is 135/85 mmHg. There is marked tenderness on deep pressure over the right costovertebral angle and on deep abdominal palpation. Urinalysis shows a pH of 7.5, specific gravity 1.020, 1+ hematuria, and no protein, glucose, or ketones. Microscopic examination of the urine shows many RBCs, WBCs, and triple phosphate crystals. Which of the following renal lesions is most likely to be present?","answers":[{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Malignant nephrosclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Papillary necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal cell carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Staghorn calculus","bool":true}],"id":482},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Normal blood levels of urea and creatinine is critical for survival. What are the raised levels of urea and creatinine with clinical features known as?","answers":[{"option":"Uremic coma","bool":false},{"option":"Azotemia","bool":false},{"option":"Renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Uremia","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic pyelonephritis","bool":false}],"id":483},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Immunologic mechanisms underlie most forms of glomerular disorders. Which of the following immunologic mechanisms of glomerular injuries is most common?","answers":[{"option":"Type-1 hypersensitivty reaction","bool":false},{"option":"Antibody-mediated injury","bool":true},{"option":"Activation of alternative complement pathway","bool":false},{"option":"Cell-mediated injury","bool":false},{"option":"Activation of intrinsic coagulation pathway","bool":false}],"id":484},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 78-year-old man is admitted to a hospital due to acute urinary tract obstruction. For the past few years, he has had concurrent bouts of cystitis. Two days before being admitted to the hospital, he could not urinate at all. What is the most probable cause of bladder outlet obstruction in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Prostatic adenocarcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Nodular prostatic hyperplasia","bool":true},{"option":"Urethral stricture","bool":false},{"option":"Urothelial cell carcinoma of the bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrogenic metaplasia","bool":false}],"id":485},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 35-year-old man came to the outpatient department with complaints of repeated urinary tract infections. His urine D/R reports show pus cells = 12-15/High power field (HPF), red blood cells = 3-5/HPF, and triple phosphate crystals in the urine. Which of the following could be the cause of infection in such a case?","answers":[{"option":"Pseudomonas aeruginosa","bool":false},{"option":"Serratia","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus mirabilis","bool":true},{"option":"Klebsiella pneumoniae","bool":false},{"option":"Enterobacter","bool":false}],"id":486},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 36-year-old married lady came to the outpatient department with a history of flank pain and difficulty in micturition. She also gave a history of weakness, fever in the evening, and a feeling of ill-health. She had not been feeling like eating recently. Her urine D/R showed 25-30 pus cells/High power field (HPF). Her erythrocyte sedimentation rate was 125 in the first hour. Her culture report was negative. What could've been the cause of her illness?","answers":[{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus mirabilis","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Klebsiella pneumoniae","bool":false},{"option":"Mycobacterium tuberculosis","bool":true}],"id":487},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following research types is aimed at discovering the underlying subjective views or experiences, motives, and desires, finding reasons for human behavior (i.e., why people think or do certain things)?","answers":[{"option":"Quantitative research","bool":false},{"option":"Medical research","bool":false},{"option":"Hospital based research","bool":false},{"option":"Clinical research","bool":false},{"option":"Qualitative research","bool":true}],"id":488},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 36-year-old is diagnosed with colorectal cancer. As the treating physician, it is your duty to educate him regarding the nature of his illness and its treatment. It is supposed to be conducted in a detailed and professional manner, using simple language which he will understand. What is this process called?","answers":[{"option":"Informational care","bool":true},{"option":"Crises intervention","bool":false},{"option":"Psychotherapy","bool":false},{"option":"Research","bool":false},{"option":"Counselling","bool":false}],"id":489},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 55-year-old female patient belonging to a rural area of Balochistan presented to you in the outpatient department and was diagnosed with diabetes. She is accompanied by her 14-year-old son who speaks and understands Urdu partially while the patient does not. You need to provide informational care to the patient but the language is an obstacle. Which of the following would be the appropriate course of action in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Admit the patient till you can find a doctor who speaks their language","bool":false},{"option":"Prescribe medication and do not provide informational care","bool":false},{"option":"Provide informational care to her son","bool":false},{"option":"Ask a colleague who speaks their language to provide informational care to the patient","bool":true},{"option":"Refer her to a doctor in Balochistan","bool":false}],"id":490},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the most important investigation for differentiating between renal and pre-renal acute renal failure?","answers":[{"option":"Computed tomography (CT) pyelogram","bool":false},{"option":"Serum creatinine","bool":false},{"option":"Urine detailed report","bool":true},{"option":"Arterial blood gases","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound kidneys, ureters, and bladder (KUB)","bool":false}],"id":491},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the most common cause of acute renal injury?","answers":[{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Acute glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Pre-renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Post-renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Tubulo-interstitial nephritis","bool":false}],"id":492},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"You visit a patient in the intensive care unit. The patient is a thin elderly female with a history of femur fracture and has been bed-bound for the past 1 year. While going through her lab values, you notice a sodium concentration of 125 mmol/L. The patient is asymptomatic for the signs of hyponatremia and is euvolemic. What first step will you take after looking at the sodium?","answers":[{"option":"Repeat sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Add sodium chloride tablet","bool":false},{"option":"Free water restriction","bool":true},{"option":"Start hypertonic saline immediately","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":493},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the composition of sodium and chloride in 0.9% normal saline?","answers":[{"option":"Na 159, Cl 154","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Na 154, Cl 154","bool":true},{"option":"Na 154, Cl 150","bool":false},{"option":"Na 150, Cl 154","bool":false}],"id":494},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 10-year-old male presents with palpable purpura in the lower extremities and buttocks area. Investigations reveal a decreased glomerular filtration rate (GFR) with a nephritic picture. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Henoch-Schönlein purpura","bool":true},{"option":"Post streptococcal glomerulonephritis","bool":false}],"id":495},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the primary indication for micturating cystourethrography?","answers":[{"option":"Acute urinary tract infection","bool":false},{"option":"Vesicoureteric reflux","bool":true},{"option":"Fistula","bool":false},{"option":"Urethral trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Urethral malignancy","bool":false}],"id":496},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the gold standard for diagnosing Helicobacter pylori?","answers":[{"option":"Histopathology","bool":false},{"option":"Urease test","bool":false},{"option":"Urea breath test","bool":false},{"option":"Microbiological culture","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":497},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"In which lymph nodes does the abdominal part of the ureter drain?","answers":[{"option":"Deep inguinal nodes","bool":false},{"option":"External iliac nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Common iliac nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Paraaortic nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Internal iliac nodes","bool":false}],"id":498},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 25-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with symptoms of nephrotic syndrome. The biopsy showed normal histology with effacement of foot processes on electron microscopy. Which disease is he likely to have?","answers":[{"option":"Acute pyelonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic pyelonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"IgA nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":true}],"id":499},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following arteries supplies the upper part of the ureter?","answers":[{"option":"Internal iliac artery","bool":false},{"option":"External iliac artery","bool":false},{"option":"Common iliac artery","bool":false},{"option":"Gonadal artery","bool":false},{"option":"Renal artery","bool":true}],"id":500},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following increase in metabolic alkalosis?","answers":[{"option":"HCO3 only","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma pH and HCO3","bool":true},{"option":"Plasma pH only","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma pH and pCO2","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma pH and lactic acid","bool":false}],"id":501},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Change occurs in which part of the bladder when it is filled with urine?","answers":[{"option":"Fundus","bool":false},{"option":"Trigone","bool":false},{"option":"Body","bool":true},{"option":"Neck","bool":false},{"option":"Base","bool":false}],"id":502},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the osmolarity of the interstitial fluid in the renal medulla?","answers":[{"option":"1800 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"600 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"1200 mOsm/L","bool":true},{"option":"1000 mOsm/L","bool":false},{"option":"800 mOsm/L","bool":false}],"id":503},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"The kidneys lie at which vertebral level?","answers":[{"option":"T12-L1","bool":false},{"option":"T12-L4","bool":false},{"option":"T12-L2","bool":false},{"option":"T11-L3","bool":false},{"option":"T12-L3","bool":true}],"id":504},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"The renal medulla contains 6-8 pyramids. What is the extension of the cortex between these pyramids called?","answers":[{"option":"Minor calyx","bool":false},{"option":"Cortical columns","bool":true},{"option":"Major calyx","bool":false},{"option":"Medullary rays","bool":false},{"option":"Cortical rays","bool":false}],"id":505},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 65-year-old male presented with a complaint of dysuria. His complete urinalysis showed gram-negative rods that were non-lactose fermenting and had swarming movements. What is the most probable cause?","answers":[{"option":"Pseudomonas aeruginosa","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus vulgaris","bool":false},{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus mirabilis","bool":true},{"option":"Enterococcus faecalis","bool":false}],"id":506},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Where are specialized cells with primary and secondary processes found?","answers":[{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Macula densa","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":true},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false}],"id":507},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which urea transporter is present in the loop of Henle for urea secretion?","answers":[{"option":"UT-1","bool":false},{"option":"UT-5","bool":false},{"option":"UT-2","bool":true},{"option":"UT-3","bool":false},{"option":"UT-4","bool":false}],"id":508},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following hormones acts on the principal cells of the nephrons?","answers":[{"option":"Parathyroid hormone","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":true},{"option":"Anti-diuretic hormone","bool":false},{"option":"Angiotensin","bool":false},{"option":"Cortisol","bool":false}],"id":509},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is not true about sodium reabsorption in the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"65% of filtered load is reabsorbed","bool":false},{"option":"80% of filtered load is reabsorbed","bool":true},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Reabsorption occurs through Na⁺-H⁺ ATPase pump","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium shares the same transporter as glucose","bool":false}],"id":510},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which substances are required for the de novo synthesis of pyrimidines?","answers":[{"option":"Glutamine and aspartate","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamine, carbon dioxide, and aspartate","bool":true},{"option":"Aspartate only","bool":false},{"option":"NADH only","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamine and NADH","bool":false}],"id":511},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Increased HCO₃⁻ excretion replaces Cl⁻ in the urine due to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Increased Na⁺-H⁺ exchange","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased Na⁺-H⁺ exchange","bool":false},{"option":"Retention of acid metabolites","bool":true},{"option":"Ketoacidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Increased acid secretion","bool":false}],"id":512},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"In which part of the nephron is the Na⁺-K⁺-2Cl⁻ transporter most abundant?","answers":[{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Thin ascending limb of loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Thin descending limb of loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Thick ascending limb of loop of Henle","bool":true}],"id":513},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is the mechanism by which calcium ions are reabsorbed in the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"Transcellular route","bool":false},{"option":"Paracellular route","bool":true},{"option":"Facilitated diffusion","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary active transport","bool":false},{"option":"Active transport","bool":false}],"id":514},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A young man presents to the outpatient department with urethral discharge. Urinalysis shows neutrophils but there are no bacteria found. What is the most likely cause?","answers":[{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false},{"option":"Treponema pallidum","bool":false},{"option":"Candida albicans","bool":false},{"option":"Chlamydia trachomatis","bool":true},{"option":"Coxiella burnetii","bool":false}],"id":515},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What should be the target blood pressure of a person having chronic kidney failure with 1+ proteinuria?","answers":[{"option":"140/90 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"160/100 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"150/90 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"130/80 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"125/75 mmHg","bool":true}],"id":516},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A patient complains of dysuria, fever, urinary frequency, and hematuria. His urinalysis shows numerous white blood cells, nitrite positive, and few red blood cells. What is true about the most common causative agent?","answers":[{"option":"Catalase negative gram-positive rods","bool":false},{"option":"Gram-negative spiral rods","bool":false},{"option":"Urease positive gram-negative rods","bool":false},{"option":"Catalase positive gram-positive rods","bool":false},{"option":"Indole positive gram-negative rods","bool":true}],"id":517},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is an extrinsic cause of unilateral partial obstruction of the ureter?","answers":[{"option":"Congenital vesicoureteral reflux","bool":false},{"option":"Retroperitoneal fibrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Renal calculi","bool":false},{"option":"Ectopic fused kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Horseshoe kidney","bool":false}],"id":518},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A man came with the complaint of right lumbar pain and hematuria for four hours. Which of the following should be the choice of investigation?","answers":[{"option":"Ultrasound KUB","bool":true},{"option":"Plain radiography KUB","bool":false},{"option":"MRI scan","bool":false},{"option":"CT scan","bool":false},{"option":"X-ray KUB","bool":false}],"id":519},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 2.2x2.4 cm mass is accidentally found on ultrasound at the lower pole of the kidney. What should be the subsequent investigation of choice?","answers":[{"option":"CT scan","bool":true},{"option":"Plain radiography KUB","bool":false},{"option":"MRI pelvis","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound KUB","bool":false},{"option":"X-ray KUB","bool":false}],"id":520},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following structures holds the kidney in its position?","answers":[{"option":"Perinephric fat","bool":false},{"option":"Renal fascia","bool":false},{"option":"Collagen bundles","bool":false},{"option":"All of these","bool":true},{"option":"Paranephric fat","bool":false}],"id":521},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following urine culture results gives the diagnosis of urinary tract infection?","answers":[{"option":"100-1000 CFU/ml","bool":false},{"option":"50000-100000 CFU/ml","bool":false},{"option":"100000-200000 CFU/ml","bool":true},{"option":"1000-5000 CFU/ml","bool":false},{"option":"10000-100000 CFU/ml","bool":false}],"id":522},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"At the end of an information care session, the patient briefly summarises which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Details of the doctor","bool":false},{"option":"Details of the drug","bool":false},{"option":"Details of the disease","bool":false},{"option":"Details of the disease, drug, and doctor","bool":true}],"id":523},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following are delicate matrix-forming cells present among the glomerular capillaries, having contractile nature, and are phagocytic?","answers":[{"option":"Podocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule cells","bool":false},{"option":"Mesangial cells","bool":true},{"option":"Juxtaglomerular cells","bool":false},{"option":"Basal lamina cells","bool":false}],"id":524},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is a congenital abnormality that occurs due to the persistence of urachus resulting in an opening between the umbilicus and the urinary bladder?","answers":[{"option":"Urachal sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Urachal fistula","bool":true},{"option":"Urachal cyst","bool":false},{"option":"Urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":525},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the remnant of the urachus?","answers":[{"option":"Umbilicus","bool":false},{"option":"Medial umbilical ligament","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral umbilical ligament","bool":false},{"option":"Umbilical artery","bool":false},{"option":"Median umbilical ligament","bool":true}],"id":526},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A two-year-old boy presented with recurrent urinary tract infections. What is the most likely cause?","answers":[{"option":"Dysplastic kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Minimal change disease","bool":false},{"option":"Congenital vesicoureteral reflux","bool":true},{"option":"Horseshoe kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Polycystic kidney disease","bool":false}],"id":527},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A female patient was on antibiotic therapy for urinary tract infections. She later developed a fever and rash.  Her urine had increased eosinophils. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Renal papillary necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Acute interstitial nephritis","bool":true},{"option":"Drug induced interstitial nephritis","bool":false}],"id":528},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"One-third of total body water is found in which of the following compartments?","answers":[{"option":"Interstitial","bool":false},{"option":"Intracellular","bool":false},{"option":"Plasma","bool":false},{"option":"Intracellular and interstitial","bool":false},{"option":"Extracellular","bool":true}],"id":529},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is measured using para-amino hippuric acid?","answers":[{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Renal plasma flow","bool":true},{"option":"Glomerular filtration rate","bool":false},{"option":"Urine output","bool":false},{"option":"Renal blood flow","bool":false}],"id":530},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is incorrect about the development of the urogenital system?","answers":[{"option":"Urethral folds merge on the ventral aspect of the penile urethra","bool":false},{"option":"All statements are correct","bool":false},{"option":"Prostatic urethra is derived from the pelvic part of the urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Membranous urethra is derived from the phallic part of the urogenital sinus","bool":true},{"option":"Hypospadias is the failure of the closure of the urethral folds","bool":false}],"id":531},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following statements is correct about the urogenital system?","answers":[{"option":"Podocytes are derived from the endoderm","bool":false},{"option":"Macula densa secrete renin","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney become functional at the end of 2nd trimester","bool":false},{"option":"Distal tubules show brush border","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting ducts are derived from the mesoderm","bool":true}],"id":532},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 65-year-old man came with a complaint of recurrent flank pain. Ultrasound revealed hydronephrosis with distension of the pelvis and calyces but the bladder and ureters were normal. What is the most likely cause of his complaint?","answers":[{"option":"Ectopic fused kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Retroperitoneal fibrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Congenital vesicoureteral reflux","bool":false},{"option":"Prostatic hyperplasia","bool":true},{"option":"Horseshoe kidney","bool":false}],"id":533},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 65-year-old male came with complaints of fever, hematuria, and flank pain. He had white blood cell casts in his urine and his culture showed 10⁴ CFU/ml. What direction of investigation should be followed?","answers":[{"option":"10⁴ CFU/ml is not significant","bool":false},{"option":"Go for a pyelogram","bool":false},{"option":"Urine culture should be done again","bool":false},{"option":"Treat as a case of urinary tract infection","bool":true},{"option":"An ultrasound should be performed","bool":false}],"id":534},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Dialysis is done in end stage renal disease as a replacement for renal function. Which of the following is correct regarding it?","answers":[{"option":"Preservation of arm veins is not important","bool":false},{"option":"Long term dialysis is done by two way catheter in the central vein","bool":false},{"option":"Long term catheter is placed in the femoral vein","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Formation of arteriovenous fistula","bool":true}],"id":535},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"What is true about hemodialysis of patient with end stage renal disease?","answers":[{"option":"Can be done at home 4 times per day","bool":false},{"option":"No need for hemodialysis in acute kidney injury","bool":false},{"option":"No restriction on diet and fluid intake","bool":false},{"option":"4 hour session thrice a week","bool":true},{"option":"Screening for hepatitis C is not required","bool":false}],"id":536},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following structures is lined by transitional epithelium?","answers":[{"option":"Nephron","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary bladder","bool":true},{"option":"Prostate gland","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Urethra","bool":false}],"id":537},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which substance donates a single carbon atom in the pyrimidine ring?","answers":[{"option":"Carbon dioxide","bool":true},{"option":"Glycine","bool":false},{"option":"Tetrahydrofolate","bool":false},{"option":"Aspartate","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamate","bool":false}],"id":538},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is involved in the de novo synthesis of both purines and pyrimidines?","answers":[{"option":"Tetrahydrofolate","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamine, carbon dioxide, and aspartate","bool":true},{"option":"Aspartate","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamine","bool":false},{"option":"Glycine","bool":false}],"id":539},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Bilateral agenesis of the kidneys is associated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Polyhydramnios","bool":false},{"option":"Renal failure later in life","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Oligohydramnios","bool":true},{"option":"Hypertrophy of kidneys","bool":false}],"id":540},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following causes an increase in the glomerular filtration rate?","answers":[{"option":"Sympathetic nervous system stimulation","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary tract obstruction","bool":false},{"option":"Epinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelial derived nitric oxide","bool":true},{"option":"Angiotensin II","bool":false}],"id":541},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is synthesized by the kidney and acts on the intestine?","answers":[{"option":"Erythropoietin","bool":false},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Calcitriol","bool":true},{"option":"Parathyroid hormone","bool":false},{"option":"Calcitonin","bool":false}],"id":542},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following are interrelated processes of the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Filtration, reabsorption, and secretion","bool":true},{"option":"Filtration, secretion, and excretion","bool":false},{"option":"Filtration and excretion","bool":false},{"option":"Filtration, reabsorption, and excretion","bool":false},{"option":"Reabsorption, secretion, and excretion","bool":false}],"id":543},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which is true regrading juxtaglomerular apparatus?","answers":[{"option":"Macula densa is a part of the proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Juxtaglomerular cells secrete renin","bool":true},{"option":"Juxtaglomerular cells are found in both afferent and efferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Macula densa cells secrete renin","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false}],"id":544},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is not a congenital disease?","answers":[{"option":"Horseshoe kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Renal agenesis","bool":false},{"option":"Polycystic kidney disease","bool":false},{"option":"Renal stones","bool":true},{"option":"Medullary cystic kidney disease","bool":false}],"id":545},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"Sodium ions are reabsorbed in exchange of which of the following ions in the proximal convoluted tubule?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Potassium ions","bool":false},{"option":"Chloride ions","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrogen ions","bool":true},{"option":"Phosphate ions","bool":false}],"id":546},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A patient on dialysis could not find a kidney donor in the family. He is about to receive a kidney transplant from someone who is about to die. What will the donor be called?","answers":[{"option":"Genetically related donor","bool":false},{"option":"Non-related donor","bool":false},{"option":"Cadaveric donor","bool":true},{"option":"Living donor","bool":false},{"option":"Living unrelated donor","bool":false}],"id":547},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2021"],"question":"A 4-year-old boy showed signs of diffuse effacement of foot processes on electron microscopy. What is correct about the disease?","answers":[{"option":"Dramatic response to corticosteroids","bool":true},{"option":"Progression to chronic renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"None of these","bool":false},{"option":"Spike and dome appearance","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of immune complex deposits","bool":false}],"id":548},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following arteries is responsible for the arterial supply to the proximal part of the ureter?","answers":[{"option":"Common iliac","bool":false},{"option":"Renal","bool":true},{"option":"Gonadal","bool":false},{"option":"Suprarenal","bool":false},{"option":"Cystic","bool":false}],"id":549},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A 6-year-old female is brought to the urology clinic with the complaint of urinary incontinence. Further investigation revealed that the urine was not coming from the bladder, but was continuously dribbling from the vagina. What is the most appropriate diagnosis for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Ectopic bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Ectopic kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Supernumerary kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive polycystic kidney disease","bool":false},{"option":"Ectopic ureter","bool":true}],"id":550},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Microscopically the Bowman's capsule comprises an inner visceral layer and an outer parietal layer. Cells lining the visceral layer have a star-shaped body with primary and secondary processes. Which of the following cells best fits this description?","answers":[{"option":"Mesangial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Brush cells","bool":false},{"option":"Podocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Simple cuboidal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelial cells","bool":false}],"id":551},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which part of the urogenital sinus gives rise to the urethra in females?","answers":[{"option":"Widest part of the urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Tip of the urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Phallic part of the urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic part of the urogenital sinus","bool":true},{"option":"Vesical part of the urogenital sinus","bool":false}],"id":552},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"In a healthy individual, what percentage of renal plasma flow would you expect to be passed into the glomerular capsule?","answers":[{"option":"Between 75 and 80%","bool":false},{"option":"Greater than 90%","bool":false},{"option":"Between 15 and 20%","bool":true},{"option":"Between 45 and 50%","bool":false},{"option":"Less than 5%","bool":false}],"id":553},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following structures is most involved in concentrating the urine?","answers":[{"option":"Superficial nephrons","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerulus","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Juxtamedullary nephron","bool":true},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false}],"id":554},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which type of transport is exhibited by the Na-K-2Cl transporter in the apical membrane of the thick ascending loop of Henle?","answers":[{"option":"Facilitated diffusion","bool":false},{"option":"Primary active transport","bool":false},{"option":"Counter transport","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary active transport","bool":true},{"option":"Passive transport","bool":false}],"id":555},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"What is the tonicity of urine as it enters the renal collecting duct?","answers":[{"option":"Hypotonic or isotonic, but never hypertonic","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotonic","bool":true},{"option":"Hypertonic or isotonic, but never hypotonic","bool":false},{"option":"Isotonic","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertonic","bool":false}],"id":556},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"All of the glucose is absorbed by the proximal convoluted tubule. Approximately 90% is in the first part of the proximal convoluted tubule. Which of the following transporters is responsible for transporting the major amount of glucose from the tubular lumen into the cell?","answers":[{"option":"SGLT 2","bool":true},{"option":"GLUT 2","bool":false},{"option":"GLUT 4","bool":false},{"option":"SGLT 1","bool":false},{"option":"GLUT 1","bool":false}],"id":557},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A substance \"X\" has the following properties:\r\nUrinary concentration (U) = 0 mg/ml Plasma concentration (P) = 13.6 mg/ml.\r\nIf a patient has a urinary flow rate (V) of 2 ml/min, what is the renal clearance rate of X?","answers":[{"option":"13.6 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"2 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"1 ml/min","bool":false},{"option":"0 ml/min","bool":true},{"option":"0.5 ml/min","bool":false}],"id":558},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"If a patient has a glomerular filtration rate of 100 ml/min and is known to be clearing a therapeutic drug at a rate of 150 ml/min, what is the most appropriate comment regarding the renal processing of this drug?","answers":[{"option":"Tm of drug has been exceeded, causing clearance to rise above GFR","bool":false},{"option":"Overall processing of this drug is similar to amino acids","bool":false},{"option":"Since the clearance is greater than GFR, the drug must be secreted","bool":true},{"option":"Since the clearance is greater than GFR, the drug must be reabsorbed","bool":false},{"option":"No evaluation can be made without further information","bool":false}],"id":559},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A one-year-old boy presents to the emergency with a complaint of weakness and growth retardation. He is lethargic and anemic. Blood analysis reveals megaloblastic anemia and urinalysis shows orotic aciduria. Which of the following compounds is most likely to alleviate his symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Adenine","bool":false},{"option":"Guanine","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoxanthine","bool":false},{"option":"Thymidine","bool":false},{"option":"Uridine","bool":true}],"id":560},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A one-year-old boy was admitted to the hospital with complaints of diarrhea and vomiting. On examination, he is lethargic, and weak and on pinching the abdominal skin it goes back very slowly. Which IV fluid should be given to rehydrate the child?","answers":[{"option":"Ringer's lactate","bool":true},{"option":"Normal saline","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertonic saline","bool":false},{"option":"Haemacel","bool":false},{"option":"5% dextrose solution","bool":false}],"id":561},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A patient presents with confusion and has a sodium level of 123 mEq/l. He is diagnosed with syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion (SIADH). Which type of hyponatremia is this?","answers":[{"option":"Antivolemic","bool":false},{"option":"Pseudovolemic","bool":false},{"option":"Hypovolemic","bool":false},{"option":"Hypervolemic","bool":false},{"option":"Euvolemic","bool":true}],"id":562},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following organisms is the most common cause of community-acquired urinary tract infections?","answers":[{"option":"Klebsiella","bool":false},{"option":"Proteus mirabilis","bool":false},{"option":"Escherichia Coli","bool":true},{"option":"Streptococcus faecalis","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus saprophyticus","bool":false}],"id":563},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is least frequently associated with focal segmental glomerulosclerosis?","answers":[{"option":"IgM deposition on immunofluorescence","bool":false},{"option":"Some glomeruli are sclerosed","bool":false},{"option":"IgA deposition on immunofluorescence","bool":true},{"option":"Nephrotic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Some glomeruli are normal","bool":false}],"id":564},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Anti-glomerular basement membrane antibody-induced glomerulonephritis accounts for less than 5% cases of human glomerulonephritis. Which of the following is the most appropriate example of this nephropathy?","answers":[{"option":"Mesangioproliferative nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Membranous nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Membranoproliferative nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Proliferation nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Crescentic nephropathy","bool":true}],"id":565},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is least likely to be seen in nephrotic syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Hematuria","bool":true},{"option":"Heavy proteinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Selective proteinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased plasma colloid osmotic pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoalbuminemia","bool":false}],"id":566},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is least likely to be correct about xanthogranulomatous pyelonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Grossly resembles renal cell carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Rare form of chronic pyelonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Associated with polyomavirus infection","bool":true},{"option":"Accumulation of foamy macrophages with plasma cells, lymphocytes and giant cells","bool":false},{"option":"Shows large yellow nodules","bool":false}],"id":567},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following statements is most appropriate regarding renal transplantation?","answers":[{"option":"ABO compatibility between donor and recipient is essential","bool":true},{"option":"Immunosuppressant drugs are prescribed to selected transplant patients","bool":false},{"option":"HLA compatibility for minor antigens is not required","bool":false},{"option":"Allergen test is performed on potential recipient","bool":false},{"option":"HLA compatibility is sometimes not required","bool":false}],"id":568},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A researcher is conducting a research study to find the prevalence of diabetes mellitus in Karachi city. Which of the following epidemiological study design is the most appropriate for this research?","answers":[{"option":"Cohort study","bool":false},{"option":"Case-control study","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional study","bool":true},{"option":"Case series","bool":false},{"option":"Experimental study","bool":false}],"id":569},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"During your posting in the behavioral sciences department, you were taught about informational care and how sharing the patient's personal information is sometimes important for the patient's care. Which of the following individuals is \"authorized\" to know the patient's personal information?","answers":[{"option":"A colleague of the patient","bool":false},{"option":"Another worker from the care team providing support to the individual","bool":true},{"option":"A senior worker not involved in supporting the individual","bool":false},{"option":"A family member of the patient","bool":false},{"option":"Another health worker from another team providing care to another individual","bool":false}],"id":570},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A patient presents to the emergency room with complaints of diarrhea and vomiting for one day. He is semi-conscious and severely dehydrated. What is the first-line management in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"IV antibiotics","bool":false},{"option":"IV fluid replacement","bool":true},{"option":"Oral antibiotics","bool":false},{"option":"KYB diet","bool":false},{"option":"Oral fluid replacement","bool":false}],"id":571},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"In a patient with severe dehydration, which organ/s become/s non-functional almost immediately?","answers":[{"option":"Eyes","bool":false},{"option":"Liver","bool":false},{"option":"Kidneys","bool":true},{"option":"Pancreas","bool":false},{"option":"Lungs","bool":false}],"id":572},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is a cause of pre-renal acute kidney failure?","answers":[{"option":"Prostrate hypertrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Profuse diarrhea","bool":true},{"option":"Nephrotic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Prostate cancer","bool":false},{"option":"Acute glomerulonephritis","bool":false}],"id":573},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A 65-year-old female with chronic kidney disease secondary to hypertension has low erythropoietin levels. Which of the following conditions is the patient at risk of developing?","answers":[{"option":"Anemia","bool":true},{"option":"Hypomagnesemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypophosphatemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypokalemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypercalcemia","bool":false}],"id":574},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"What is the investigation of choice to diagnose vesicoureteric reflux in a male toddler?","answers":[{"option":"IV urography","bool":false},{"option":"CT urography","bool":false},{"option":"MR urethrography","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound bladder with pre and post void volumes","bool":false},{"option":"Micturating cystourethrography","bool":true}],"id":575},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following vessels gives rise to the renal arteries?","answers":[{"option":"Lobar artery","bool":false},{"option":"Gonadal vein","bool":false},{"option":"Abdominal aorta","bool":true},{"option":"Common iliac artery","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior vena cava","bool":false}],"id":576},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following structures enters the kidney at the hilum and brings blood to the kidneys?","answers":[{"option":"Abdominal aorta","bool":false},{"option":"Common iliac artery","bool":false},{"option":"Renal vein","bool":false},{"option":"Renal artery","bool":true},{"option":"Inferior vena cava","bool":false}],"id":577},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following are direct branches of the renal arteries?","answers":[{"option":"Afferent arteries","bool":false},{"option":"Lobar arteries","bool":false},{"option":"Segmental arteries","bool":true},{"option":"Lobular arteries","bool":false},{"option":"Arcuate arteries","bool":false}],"id":578},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which part of the renal tubule is impermeable to water, while solutes can pass out passively into medullary interstitial space?","answers":[{"option":"Thin ascending limb of loop of Henle","bool":true},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Thick ascending limb of loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Descending limb of loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":579},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"In which segment of the renal tubule are the sodium-hydrogen antiporters that are involved in hydrogen ion secretion located?","answers":[{"option":"Loop of Henle - thin segment","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting duct","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle - thick segment","bool":false}],"id":580},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A 46-year-old male presents to the emergency room with severe right toe pain. On examination, he had a temperature of 100.8° F, and he was moderately distressed about the pain in his toe. The right big toe was swollen, warm, red, and exquisitely tender. Synovial joint fluid was obtained and revealed rod or needle-shaped crystals. Which enzyme(s) is/are deficient in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyl transferase","bool":true},{"option":"Alkaline phosphatase, Phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyl transferase, Phosphoribosyl pyrophosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Adenosine deaminase, Hypoxanthine-guanine phosphoribosyl transferase","bool":false}],"id":581},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following best describes the urine of diabetic patients?","answers":[{"option":"Decreased volume, increased specific gravity","bool":false},{"option":"Increased volume, increased specific gravity","bool":true},{"option":"Increased volume, decreased specific gravity","bool":false},{"option":"Normal volume, increased specific gravity","bool":false},{"option":"Normal volume, decreased specific gravity","bool":false}],"id":582},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following serves as a cofactor in de novo purine synthesis?","answers":[{"option":"Folate","bool":true},{"option":"Thiamine","bool":false},{"option":"Biotin","bool":false},{"option":"Flavin","bool":false},{"option":"Caltrate","bool":false}],"id":583},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A 60-year-old male with a history of diabetes and chronic kidney failure presents to the clinic with complaints of dyspnea, cough, malaise, and fever for 15 days. How can the glomerular filtration rate be determined in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Urinalysis","bool":false},{"option":"Serum pyruvate dehydrogenase","bool":false},{"option":"IV pyelogram","bool":false},{"option":"Renal scan","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine clearance","bool":true}],"id":584},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A 55-year-old male with COPD presents to the clinic with increased severity of shortness of breath. His immediate arterial blood gases show respiratory acidosis. What is the first step in the interpretation of arterial blood gases?","answers":[{"option":"PaCO₂","bool":false},{"option":"Anion gap","bool":false},{"option":"HCO₃ level","bool":false},{"option":"pH of blood","bool":true},{"option":"Delta-delta gap","bool":false}],"id":585},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A 40-year-old female with a history of breast carcinoma was brought to the critical care unit with the complication of metastasis. They were counseled about minimal chances of survival. The family was not convinced by your opinion and wished to consult a second specialist. What is the responsibility of the doctor in this scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Offer psychoeducation","bool":false},{"option":"Offer palliative care","bool":false},{"option":"Support the decision of second opinion","bool":true},{"option":"Discharge the patient immediately","bool":false},{"option":"Facilitate by counseling","bool":false}],"id":586},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"What percentage of the total body weight does the extra-cellular fluid (ECF) account for?","answers":[{"option":"15%","bool":false},{"option":"10%","bool":false},{"option":"70%","bool":false},{"option":"5%","bool":false},{"option":"20%","bool":true}],"id":587},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"The renal sinus is a space within the kidney containing all the structures responsible for draining urine into the ureter. Which of the following structures is present in this space?","answers":[{"option":"Major calyx","bool":true},{"option":"Renal pyramids","bool":false},{"option":"Renal medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Cortical columns","bool":false},{"option":"Medullary rays","bool":false}],"id":588},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common site for an ectopic kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Upper abdomen","bool":false},{"option":"Perineum","bool":false},{"option":"Inguinal canal","bool":false},{"option":"Lower abdomen","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvis","bool":true}],"id":589},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following results in an uninhibited neurogenic bladder?","answers":[{"option":"Pelvic nerve injury","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary tract infection","bool":false},{"option":"Partial injury of spinal cord or brainstem","bool":true},{"option":"Tabes dorsalis","bool":false},{"option":"Spinal cord injury above sacral region","bool":false}],"id":590},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"The parents of an 11-year-old mentally impaired male child visit a local clinic. The father tells the doctor that he has 7 other children to support and someone suggested that he could sell the kidney of his mentally impaired son. What is the correct legal implication in this case according to the \"Transplantation of Human Organs and Tissues Act 2010\"?","answers":[{"option":"It is illegal to sell a kidney and should not be done","bool":true},{"option":"It is legal because patient is mentally impaired","bool":false},{"option":"It can only be donated to a relative","bool":false},{"option":"It can be sold since parents provide their consent","bool":false},{"option":"Consent of patient is needed","bool":false}],"id":591},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"The enzyme carbonic anhydrase catalyzes the formation of which of the following compounds?","answers":[{"option":"H₃PO₄","bool":false},{"option":"H₂CO₃","bool":true},{"option":"H₂PO₄","bool":false},{"option":"H₂SO₄","bool":false},{"option":"HNO₃","bool":false}],"id":592},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"The Na-K-2Cl cotransporters are present in which of the following parts of a nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Thick ascending limb of loop of Henle","bool":true},{"option":"Descending limb of loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Thin descending limb of loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":593},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"The synthesis of deoxyribonucleotides from ribonucleotides requires the enzyme ribonucleotide reductase. Which of the following is a cofactor for this enzyme?","answers":[{"option":"Riboflavin","bool":false},{"option":"Thioredoxin","bool":true},{"option":"Pyridoxine","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Folate","bool":false}],"id":594},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common route of spread of acute pyelonephritis?","answers":[{"option":"Direct spread from nearby viscera","bool":false},{"option":"From peritoneal cavity","bool":false},{"option":"Ascending spread from urethra and bladder","bool":true},{"option":"Hematogenous spread","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphogenous spread","bool":false}],"id":595},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"In the process of pyrimidine metabolism, the deamination of cytosine produces which of the following compounds?","answers":[{"option":"Uracil","bool":true},{"option":"Thiouracil","bool":false},{"option":"Cytidylic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Thiamine","bool":false},{"option":"Adenylic acid","bool":false}],"id":596},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A doctor is performing a nephrostomy. Which of the following regions of the body is most appropriate to approach the kidney?","answers":[{"option":"Anterior abdominal wall","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic cavity","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior abdominal wall","bool":true},{"option":"Inferior part of pelvic cavity","bool":false},{"option":"Superior part of the pelvic cavity","bool":false}],"id":597},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following factors help distinguish that hematuria is of renal origin and not from the bladder?","answers":[{"option":"RBC casts","bool":true},{"option":"Hemoglobinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Sterile pyuria","bool":false},{"option":"WBC casts","bool":false},{"option":"Gross hematuria","bool":false}],"id":598},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Under the action of which of the following hormones is potassium secreted from the principal cells of the late distal tubules and collecting ducts?","answers":[{"option":"Angiotensin I","bool":false},{"option":"Cortisol","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone","bool":true},{"option":"Angiotensin II","bool":false},{"option":"Antidiuretic hormone","bool":false}],"id":599},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following ions is secreted by the principal cells when stimulated by aldosterone?","answers":[{"option":"H⁺","bool":false},{"option":"Na⁺","bool":false},{"option":"Cl⁻","bool":false},{"option":"Ca⁺","bool":false},{"option":"K⁺","bool":true}],"id":600},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following nerves supplies the sensory innervation to the bladder?","answers":[{"option":"Sacral nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic nerve","bool":true},{"option":"Pudendal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Hypogastric nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic splanchnic nerve","bool":false}],"id":601},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most commonly used test to assess renal function?","answers":[{"option":"Para-aminohippuric acid clearance","bool":false},{"option":"Uric acid","bool":false},{"option":"Inulin clearance","bool":false},{"option":"Urea","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine clearance","bool":true}],"id":602},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following structures is most likely to be damaged during the surgical approach of kidneys around the 11th or 12th rib?","answers":[{"option":"Lesser sac of peritoneal cavity","bool":false},{"option":"Diaphragm","bool":false},{"option":"Pleura","bool":true},{"option":"Lungs","bool":false},{"option":"Pericardium","bool":false}],"id":603},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following cells associated with the glomerular capillaries are involved in phagocytosis of macromolecules, adjusting filtration rate, mediating immune response in a glomerulus, and providing structural support?","answers":[{"option":"Podocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Kupffer cells","bool":false},{"option":"Endothelial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Mesangial cells","bool":true},{"option":"Principal cells","bool":false}],"id":604},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"The decrease in sodium chloride (NaCl) concentration in the glomerular filtrate, when sensed by the macula densa is most likely to result in which of the following responses?","answers":[{"option":"Increased release of renin from juxtaglomerular cells","bool":true},{"option":"Dilation of efferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Contraction of afferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibition of renin release from juxtaglomerular cells","bool":false},{"option":"Contraction of mesangial cells","bool":false}],"id":605},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"A histopathologist observes a slide of the wall of the urinary bladder with three distinct layers the mucosa, muscularis, and serosa. Which of the following parts of the bladder is under observation?","answers":[{"option":"Superior surface","bool":true},{"option":"Trigone","bool":false},{"option":"Inferolateral surface","bool":false},{"option":"Neck","bool":false},{"option":"Fundus","bool":false}],"id":606},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following conditions results in efflux of potassium ions from the cell?","answers":[{"option":"Increased Insulin level","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis","bool":true},{"option":"β-adrenergic stimulation","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperaldosteronism","bool":false}],"id":607},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Aspartate enters the Krebs cycle as which of the following compounds?","answers":[{"option":"α-ketoglutarate","bool":false},{"option":"Succinyl CoA","bool":false},{"option":"Citrate","bool":false},{"option":"Fumarate","bool":false},{"option":"Oxaloacetate","bool":true}],"id":608},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"The pain due to a ureteric calculi can extend from the loin to the groin. This area is supplied by which of the following spinal segments?","answers":[{"option":"T12 to L3","bool":false},{"option":"S1 to S3","bool":false},{"option":"T11 to L2","bool":true},{"option":"L1 and L2","bool":false},{"option":"L1 to L3","bool":false}],"id":609},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2022"],"question":"Which of the following parts of the male urethra is lined by pseudostratified columnar epithelium?","answers":[{"option":"Bulbar urethra","bool":false},{"option":"Urethral meatus","bool":false},{"option":"Prostatic urethra","bool":false},{"option":"Membranous urethra","bool":true},{"option":"Navicular fossa","bool":false}],"id":610},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"The kidneys are supplied by blood via renal arteries which arise directly from the abdominal aorta immediately distal to the origin of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Splenic artery","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior mesenteric artery","bool":false},{"option":"Celiac trunk","bool":false},{"option":"Left gastric artery","bool":false},{"option":"Superior mesenteric artery","bool":true}],"id":611},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"During a dissection class, second-year medical students discuss facts about the covering of the kidney. Which of the following statements is true?","answers":[{"option":"Perirenal fat lies external to the renal fascia","bool":false},{"option":"Renal fascia encloses the suprarenal gland","bool":true},{"option":"Pararenal fat continues with fascia iliaca","bool":false},{"option":"Perirenal fat continues with fascia transversalis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal fascia directly covers the kidney","bool":false}],"id":612},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"The fusion of the lower pole of the kidney, causing the ureters to pass anterior to the isthmus of the kidney, is referred to as which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Rosette kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Unilateral double kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Aberrant kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Horseshoe kidney","bool":true}],"id":613},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"The trigone of the urinary bladder develops from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Phallic part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Absorbed mesonephric duct","bool":true},{"option":"Vesical part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic part of urogenital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Paramesonephric duct","bool":false}],"id":614},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 35-year-old male patient comes to the emergency department with a complaint of throbbing pain in the left loin radiating towards the ipsilateral groin. On radiological investigation, a ureteric calculus is seen. The calculus is likely to be lodged at which of the following sites?","answers":[{"option":"Uretero-pelvic junction","bool":true},{"option":"Trigone of the bladder","bool":false},{"option":"Renal medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Pelvic outlet","bool":false},{"option":"Renal papilla","bool":false}],"id":615},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"The lymphatics from the middle part of the ureter drain into which of the following groups of lymph nodes?","answers":[{"option":"Celiac nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Common iliac nodes","bool":true},{"option":"Hepatic nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Para-aortic group","bool":false},{"option":"Internal iliac nodes","bool":false}],"id":616},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Which of the following structures plays a key role in the countercurrent multiplication mechanism for concentrating urine in the nephron?","answers":[{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Loop of Henle","bool":true},{"option":"Vasa Recta","bool":false},{"option":"Bowman's capsule","bool":false}],"id":617},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"What type of transport mechanism exemplifies the sodium-potassium-chloride (Na-K-2Cl) transporter located on the apical membrane in the thick ascending limb of the Loop of Henle?","answers":[{"option":"Passive transport","bool":false},{"option":"Counter transport","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary active transport","bool":true},{"option":"Facilitated diffusion","bool":false},{"option":"Primary active transport","bool":false}],"id":618},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 65-year-old male is admitted to the hospital with symptoms of confusion, hyponatremia, and concentrated urine. The patient's medical history includes lung cancer and recent chemotherapy. Laboratory tests reveal low serum sodium levels and high urine osmolality. What is the most likely cause of the patient's symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Syndrome of inappropriate ADH secretion","bool":true},{"option":"Hyperaldosteronism","bool":false},{"option":"Renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes insipidus","bool":false},{"option":"Dehydration","bool":false}],"id":619},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 55-year-old female undergoes a renal clearance test to assess the clearance of a substance that is freely filtered at the glomerulus and neither reabsorbed nor secreted by the renal tubules. The clearance value for this substance is found to be equal to the patient's glomerular filtration rate (GFR). Which of the following substances is most likely being measured in this test?","answers":[{"option":"Creatinine","bool":false},{"option":"Urea","bool":false},{"option":"Inulin","bool":true},{"option":"Sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose","bool":false}],"id":620},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 55-year-old male is admitted to the hospital with complaints of excessive thirst and polyuria (excessive urine production). Laboratory tests reveal low urine osmolarity. Which of the following is the most likely explanation for the patient's symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Reduced secretion of renin","bool":false},{"option":"Excessive release of aldosterone","bool":false},{"option":"Increased reabsorption of Na+ in the proximal tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Impaired release of antidiuretic hormone","bool":true},{"option":"Inadequate glomerular filtration rate","bool":false}],"id":621},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Which of the following glucose transporters is primarily responsible for 90% of glucose reabsorption from the brush border epithelium of proximal convoluted tubules?","answers":[{"option":"SGLT1","bool":false},{"option":"SGLT2","bool":true},{"option":"GLUT3","bool":false},{"option":"GLUT2","bool":false},{"option":"GLUT1","bool":false}],"id":622},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A research group is studying the functions of specific transporters in the renal tubules to assess their role in maintaining homeostasis. In this context, which of the following functions should be investigated to determine the primary role of pendrin in the renal tubules?","answers":[{"option":"Regulating blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Facilitating glucose reabsorption","bool":false},{"option":"Maintaining acid-base balance","bool":true},{"option":"Reabsorbing sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Enhancing water reabsorption","bool":false}],"id":623},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 42-year-old female is being treated for hypertension and is prescribed a diuretic that inhibits sodium reabsorption in the early distal convoluted tubule. Which type of diuretic is most likely being used?","answers":[{"option":"Carbonic anhydrase inhibitor","bool":false},{"option":"Loop diuretic","bool":false},{"option":"Thiazide diuretic","bool":true},{"option":"Osmotic diuretic","bool":false},{"option":"Aldosterone antagonist","bool":false}],"id":624},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Which segment of the renal tubule is water impermeable, allowing solutes like sodium and chloride to passively diffuse into the medullary interstitial space?","answers":[{"option":"Distal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Thin ascending limb loop of Henle","bool":true},{"option":"Descending limb loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Thick ascending limb loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":625},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the most abundant closed buffer in the proximal tubular fluid?","answers":[{"option":"Bicarbonate","bool":true},{"option":"Lactate","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphate","bool":false},{"option":"Ammonia","bool":false},{"option":"Proteins","bool":false}],"id":626},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A patient is undergoing a renal function test to determine the clearance of substance X. After a urine collection period, it is found that the concentration of substance X in urine (U) is 200 mg/dL, the concentration of substance X in plasma (P) is 20 mg/dL, and the urine flow rate (V) is 1.2 mL/min. What would be the renal clearance of substance X?","answers":[{"option":"C= 12 mL/min","bool":true},{"option":"C= 2 mL/min","bool":false},{"option":"C= 0.1 mL/min","bool":false},{"option":"C= 1200 mL/min","bool":false},{"option":"C= 200 mL/min","bool":false}],"id":627},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Two samples of filtrate are taken from the beginning and end of the proximal tubules by a micropipette for comparison. Which one of the following substances would be present in large quantity at the end as compared to the beginning?","answers":[{"option":"Amino acids","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Chloride","bool":true},{"option":"Sodium","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium","bool":false}],"id":628},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"In an experiment, 5 grams of substance A is found to be filtered at the glomeruli per day, while 7 grams of the same substance is excreted in urine per day. Which one of the following statements justifies the above condition?","answers":[{"option":"All of that substance is reabsorbed","bool":false},{"option":"Substance is both reabsorbed and secreted","bool":false},{"option":"Rate of filtration equals rate of excretion","bool":false},{"option":"Substance is synthesized in the tubular cells","bool":false},{"option":"Substance is secreted by the nephron","bool":true}],"id":629},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Which blood vessels surround the loops of Henle?","answers":[{"option":"Efferent arterioles","bool":false},{"option":"Interlobular arteries","bool":false},{"option":"Peritubular capillaries","bool":false},{"option":"Vasa recta","bool":true},{"option":"Interlobar arteries","bool":false}],"id":630},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Cytidine triphosphate (CTP) is produced by the amination of UTP (Uridine triphosphate) by which one of the following enzymes?","answers":[{"option":"UTP transferase","bool":false},{"option":"CTP synthetase","bool":true},{"option":"Ribonucleotide reductase","bool":false},{"option":"CTP synthase","bool":false},{"option":"CTP kinase","bool":false}],"id":631},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 3-month-old infant was brought to the outpatient department with a complaint of an eczematous rash along with vomiting. In addition, he had a musty and mousy odor in his urine. The infant had blond hair, blue eyes along with fair skin. Which of the following diseases is most likely to be linked in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Phenylketonuria","bool":true},{"option":"Cystinuria","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetic ketoacidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Maple syrup disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Glycinuria","bool":false}],"id":632},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Many substances are cleared by the kidney. Under normal physiological conditions the clearance of which of the following substances is zero?","answers":[{"option":"Inulin","bool":false},{"option":"Creatinine","bool":false},{"option":"Glucose","bool":true},{"option":"Phenolphthalein","bool":false},{"option":"PAH","bool":false}],"id":633},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Which one of the following actions is inhibited by parathyroid hormone in the renal tubules?","answers":[{"option":"Phosphate secretion in proximal tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium reabsorption in distal tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Phosphate reabsorption in proximal tubule","bool":true},{"option":"Potassium secretion in distal tubule","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium reabsorption in loop of Henle","bool":false}],"id":634},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A healthy 25-year-old male participates in a marathon race on a hot and humid day and becomes dehydrated. In which of the following segments of his nephron, maximum water will be reabsorbed in the presence of high levels of antidiuretic hormone (ADH)?","answers":[{"option":"Descending limb of Loop of Henle","bool":false},{"option":"Distal convoluted tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Proximal convoluted tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting tubules","bool":false},{"option":"Collecting ducts","bool":true}],"id":635},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"The arterial blood gas (ABG) analysis of a 44-year-old female with a history of severe diarrhea showed a pH of 7.25, PCO2= 24 mmHg, HCO3= 10mEq/L, and K+= 2.5mEq/l. Which one of the following conditions is the most appropriate diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Normal status","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis","bool":true},{"option":"Respiratory alkalosis","bool":false}],"id":636},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"What is the net filtration pressure at the glomerulus if the glomerular hydrostatic pressure is 44 mmHg, Bowman's capsule hydrostatic pressure is 9mmHg, the osmotic pressure of plasma is 28mmHg, and the osmotic pressure of the tubular fluid is 0mmHg?","answers":[{"option":"14 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"11 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"7 mmHg","bool":true},{"option":"18 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"21 mmHg","bool":false}],"id":637},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 35-year-old female with uncontrolled diabetes was found to have a plasma glucose level of 300 mg/dl with a normal glomerular filtration rate. Which one of the following values corresponds to the calculated filtered load of glucose in this case?","answers":[{"option":"250 mg/dl","bool":false},{"option":"575 mg/dl","bool":false},{"option":"450 mg/dl","bool":false},{"option":"150 mg/dl","bool":false},{"option":"375 mg/dl","bool":true}],"id":638},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"In muscle tissue, creatine and phosphocreatine produce creatinine as a waste product excreted from the body. The creatinine clearance test is that it is the marker of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Tubular function","bool":false},{"option":"Glomerular function","bool":true},{"option":"Urolithiasis","bool":false},{"option":"Measurement of skeletal muscle mass","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder function","bool":false}],"id":639},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"In tissues that do not carry out active de novo synthesis, how is an adequate supply of adenine nucleotides maintained?","answers":[{"option":"It requires ATP uptake from the blood","bool":false},{"option":"It is accomplished entirely by the action of adenylate kinase","bool":false},{"option":"It depends upon the action of nucleoside phosphorylase","bool":false},{"option":"It involves hypoxanthine salvage using HG-PRT","bool":false},{"option":"It occurs primarily by adenine salvage using A-PRT","bool":true}],"id":640},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 55-year-old man presents with hypertension, puffiness of his face, and darkening of urine. Serum levels of blood urea nitrogen (BUN) are raised. Urinalysis reports numerous RBCs and occasional red cell casts. He was admitted for further investigations. Which of the following serum proteins will be found depleted in this patient suggesting an immune-complex mediated renal involvement?","answers":[{"option":"Complement C3","bool":true},{"option":"Albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Hageman factor (factor XII)","bool":false},{"option":"Amyloid","bool":false}],"id":641},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy abruptly develops malaise, fever, nausea, oliguria, and hematuria (smoky or cola-colored urine) one to two weeks after recovery from a sore throat. The patient has red cell casts in the urine, mild proteinuria (< 1 gm/day), periorbital edema, and mild to moderate hypertension. Which of the following best describes this patient's medical condition?","answers":[{"option":"Rapidly progressive glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Polycystic kidneys","bool":false},{"option":"Membranous glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrotic syndrome","bool":false}],"id":642},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 7-year-old boy has been diagnosed with post-infectious glomerulonephritis resulting in nephritic syndrome. The child has hematuria as a part of this syndrome. Which of the following findings on urinalysis would suggest that RBCs in his urine are coming from the kidneys and not from lower down the urinary tract?","answers":[{"option":"White cell casts","bool":false},{"option":"Red cell casts","bool":true},{"option":"Urobilinogen","bool":false},{"option":"Blood clots","bool":false},{"option":"Macrophages containing red cells","bool":false}],"id":643},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"Muscle-invasive bladder cancers are associated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Amplification of c-myc gene","bool":false},{"option":"Inactivation of TP53 & Rb tumor suppressor genes","bool":true},{"option":"Activations of TP53 & RB tumor suppressor genes","bool":false},{"option":"Translocation of TFE3 gene","bool":false},{"option":"Gene notations of MET proto-oncogene","bool":false}],"id":644},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 42-year-old man has had recurrent episodes of urinary tract infections (UTIs) over the last six months. Urine culture has yielded the growth of Proteus mirabilis on three occasions. Which one of the following could be the most likely underlying cause?","answers":[{"option":"Reflux nephropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Enterovesical fistula","bool":false},{"option":"Schistosomiasis","bool":false},{"option":"Prostatitis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal calculi","bool":true}],"id":645},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A patient with severe recurrent gout, who had been taking high doses of analgesics, presented with malaise and nausea. Laboratory findings showed raised serum urea and creatinine levels. Which one of the following diseases is he suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Renal papillary necrosis","bool":true},{"option":"Hydronephrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute tubular injury","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic glomerulonephritis","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrolithiasis","bool":false}],"id":646},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 45-year-old man had left flank pain. Ultrasonography showed bilaterally enlarged kidneys with multiple variable-size cysts in both the cortex and medulla. A few cysts in the liver were also seen. What is the most likely pattern of inheritance of this disease?","answers":[{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":true},{"option":"Cytogenetic disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal co-dominant","bool":false}],"id":647},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"An elderly patient with a history of heart disease has difficulty breathing and is diagnosed with acute pulmonary edema. Which of the following drugs is indicated as a drug of first choice to treat this problem?","answers":[{"option":"Mannitol","bool":false},{"option":"Spironolactone","bool":false},{"option":"Chlorthalidone","bool":false},{"option":"Acetazolamide","bool":false},{"option":"Furosemide","bool":true}],"id":648},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A patient was referred to your clinic by a physician with a note that the patient's chronic illness is not improving despite getting all treatment options for his illness. Evaluate the patient and share your expert opinion. What steps would you like to consider in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Ensure compliance of patient","bool":false},{"option":"Evaluate the risk factors and barriers of treatment adherence","bool":true},{"option":"Guide the caregiver for adherence","bool":false},{"option":"Address the issues of patient","bool":false},{"option":"Change in medicine/drug regime","bool":false}],"id":649},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 34-year-old female presented to the outpatient department with decreased urination and pedal edema. On examination, there was a renal bruit on the right side. Her blood pressure was 160/100 mmHg. Her primary care physician prescribed her antihypertensive medication a week ago. Her investigations revealed a Hb of 12.1 gm/dl, urea 109 mg/dl, creatinine 4.2 mg/dl, Na⁺ 138 mEq/l, K⁺ 5.4 mEq/L. Which of the following antihypertensive must have been prescribed to her which resulted in increased serum creatinine level?","answers":[{"option":"Beta blockers","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha blockers","bool":false},{"option":"Thiazide diuretics","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium channel blockers","bool":false},{"option":"ACE inhibitors","bool":true}],"id":650},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 26-year-old female presented to the outpatient department with loose watery stools for 2 days, occurring almost 10-15 episodes per day. It was not associated with fever or blood in stools. On examination, she was severely dehydrated and had decreased urinary output. Her investigations showed a Hb of 15.9 gm/dl, MCV 92, platelets 162 × 10⁹, urea 112 mg/dl, creatinine 4.2 mg/dl, Na⁺ 136 mEq/l, K⁺ 4.2 mEq/L, HCO₃⁻: 16 mEq/L. What should be the immediate treatment?","answers":[{"option":"Adequate hydration","bool":true},{"option":"Oral-rehydration salt (ORS)","bool":false},{"option":"Antibiotics","bool":false},{"option":"Bicarbonate replacement","bool":false},{"option":"Hemodialysis","bool":false}],"id":651},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 68-year-old male presented with decreased urinary output and pedal edema for 6 months. He has been diabetic for 30 years and has recently started developing recurrent hypoglycemia. Which of the following tests is most pertinent for establishing chronic kidney disease?","answers":[{"option":"Urine DR for proteinuria","bool":false},{"option":"eGFR","bool":true},{"option":"Electrolytes and arterial blood gases (ABGs)","bool":false},{"option":"Serum albumin","bool":false},{"option":"Urea and creatinine","bool":false}],"id":652},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old male presents in the emergency department with upper abdominal pain for the last 2 days and gradual deterioration in consciousness over the last 6 hours. He has been previously well. On examination, his blood pressure in 100/70mmHg, pulse 130/minute, respiratory rate 30/min with rapid and deep breathing, and he was afebrile. Arterial blood gas shows pH 7.10, PCO₂ 20 mmHg, PO₂ 60 mmHg, HCO₃ 6 meq/L. What is the acid-base disorder in this scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Respiratory alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis","bool":true},{"option":"No acid-base disturbance","bool":false}],"id":653},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old male presents in the emergency department with sudden loss of consciousness after ingesting some unknown compound. He had been previously well. On examination, his blood pressure is 100/70mmHg, pulse 90/minute, respiratory rate 6/min, and he is afebrile. He is not following commands and does not open his eyes to pain even. Arterial blood gas shows a pH of 7.10, PCO₂ 80 mmHg, PO₂ 60 mmHg, HCO₃, 27 mEq/L. What is the acid-base disorder in this scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Respiratory acidosis","bool":true},{"option":"Respiratory alkalosis","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis with increase anion-gap","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic acidosis","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic alkalosis","bool":false}],"id":654},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 50-year-old male patient has presented with sudden-onset, severe watery diarrhea that has persisted for four days. He experiences approximately 15 episodes of diarrhea per day and also vomiting. There is no blood in the stool. Upon examination, he has marked dehydration, a temperature of 38.5 °C, and a rapid heart rate. Which of the following electrolyte imbalances is he at risk of developing?","answers":[{"option":"Hypocalcemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hyponatremia","bool":true},{"option":"Hypernatremia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypokalemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperkalemia","bool":false}],"id":655},{"info":["2nd-year/renal/compiled","2nd-year/renal/2023"],"question":"A 54-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with a history of recurrent headaches due to sinusitis, for which he took non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) regularly. His initial investigations showed a Hb of 11.2 gm/dl, a total leukocyte count (TLC) of 4.8 ×10 ³, 58% neutrophils, 28% lymphocytes, 12% eosinophils, and 2% monocytes. Urea is 98 mg/dl and creatinine is 2.1 gm/dl. Urine analysis is positive for protein. What is the most likely reason for his deranged laboratory tests?","answers":[{"option":"Interstitial nephritis","bool":true},{"option":"Nephritic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrotic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"End-stage renal disease","bool":false},{"option":"Acute tubular necrosis","bool":false}],"id":656}]
export default arr